<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="98"><page Index="1"><![CDATA["Let  u s   leave  a saint  to write the  life  of a saint,"  is   said  to
               have  been  the  exclamation  of  the  Angelic  Doctor  S t.
               Thomas  Aquinas,  when  he  entered  the cell  of  his  brother
               doctor, S t .  Bonaventure, and found him absorbed in writing
               the life of his spiritual father, S t.  Francis. The peculiar value
               of the present  little book is   that  it  may  be said  once more
               to present the spectacle of a saint writing the life of a saint.
               Only whereas  in  S t.  Bonaventure's  case  a son  was writing
               the life of a father,  in this case we have the unique example
               of a father writing the life of his spiritual son. The writer, the
               saintly  Don  Bosco,  h a s   already  been  declared  Venerable,
               and the process for his  Beatification is   proceeding in  Rome.
               - Preface.































                                                           1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1









                                                        9  781304  552099]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[THE LIFE OF



                          Dominic Savio





                       whose Cause (for Beatification and Canonization)
                             was introduced February 11th, 1914.








                 TRANSLATED FROM THE ORIGINAL WORK OF THE
                    VENERABLE SERVANT OF GOD, JOHN BOSCO.




                                   WITH A PREFACE BY
                          HIS LORDSHIP BISHOP CASARTELLI
                                       Bishop of Salford.







                               First published in London, 1915.]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Typographical Arrangement Copyright © 2024 E. Phang

            Printed and distributed by Lulu in the United States of America.

                             First printing edition 2024.

            The text of “The Life of Dominic Savio” is in the public domain.

             Credits: Bosco. (1915). The Life of Dominic Savio: Whose cause (for
           beatification and canonization) was introduced February 11th, 1914. Salesian
          Press. https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Life_of_Dominic_Savio
                 Cover image: Public domain, via Wikimedia Commons
           https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Z_domingo_savio.jpg


                              For Our Lady’s intentions.

                              ISBN: 978-1-304-55209-9

                  https://www.lulu.com/spotlight/gotomothermary]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Nihil Obstat:
              ⁠   F. THOMAS BERGH, O.S.B.,
                                    Censor Deputatus.


              Imprimatur:
              ⁠   ✠ PETRUS, Episcopus Southwarcensis








              In  conformity  with  the  Decree  of  Pope Urban  VIII.,  the  writer
              declares that none but human authority is claimed for whatever of a
              supernatural nature is herein contained, until the Holy See may have
              sanctioned it by its infallible authority.]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[CONTENTS


                              Preface by His Lordship
                              The Bishop of Salford               vii

                              The Author’s Preface                x

                           I  Early life                          Pg 1


                          II  Youthful virtue. School experiences   Pg 3

                         III  His First Communion at an early age  Pg 5

                         IV  Early school career                  Pg 8

                          V  At Mondonio. A calumny               Pg 11

                         VI  Don Bosco and Dominic Savio          Pg 13

                        VII  His entrance at the Oratory          Pg 15


                       VIII  His studies and conduct              Pg 17

                         IX  His resolution regarding sanctity    Pg 21

                          X  Zeal for the salvation of souls      Pg 23

                         XI  Various incidents                    Pg 26

                        XII  His spirit of prayer and
                              devotion to Our Lady                Pg 29
                       XIII  His use of the Sacraments            Pg 32]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[CONTENTS


                      XIV  Mortifications                          Pg 36

                       XV  Restraint in demeanour                  Pg 38

                      XVI  The Confraternity of the
                             Immaculate Conception                 Pg 41


                      XVII  Dominic’s intimate associates          Pg 43

                     XVIII  Dominic and John Massiglia             Pg 46

                      XIX  Special graces and particular incidents.
                             England and the Sovereign Pontiff     Pg 51

                       XX  His ideas on death                      Pg 55

                      XXI  He has to leave the Oratory             Pg 58


                      XXII  Illness. He receives the last
                             Sacraments                            Pg 62

                     XXIII  Last moments and death                 Pg 65

                     XXIV  The news of his death.
                             Remarkable testimony                  Pg 68

                      XXV  The influence of his virtues            Pg 71

              APPENDIX  Favours received through
                             his intercession                      Pg 74]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[PREFACE.

              “L
                           et us leave a saint to write the life of a saint," is said to
                           have  been  the  exclamation of  the Angelic  Doctor  St.
                           Thomas  Aquinas,  when  he  entered  the  cell  of  his
              brother doctor, St. Bonaventure, and found him absorbed in writing
              the life of his spiritual father, St. Francis.
                  The peculiar value of the present little book is that it may be said
              once  more to present  the  spectacle  of  a saint  writing  the  life of  a
              saint. Only whereas in St. Bonaventure's case a son was writing the
              life of a father, in this case we have the unique example of a father
              writing the life of his spiritual son. The writer, the saintly Don Bosco,
              has  already  been  declared  Venerable,  and  the  process  for  his
              Beatification is proceeding in Rome.
                  Little  Domenico  Savio,  whose  biography  was  originally
              published  by  Don  Bosco  very  shortly  after  the  holy  child's  death,
              was, as will be seen, Don Bosco's spiritual child, and it is a subject of
              great  joy  to  all  his  admirers  that  his  cause  also  has  at  last  been
              introduced at Rome with the approval of the Holy See.
                  The  publication  of  this  English  translation  of  the  life,  may,
              please God, contribute not a little to the successful issue of the cause
              of his beatification.
                  There  are  reasons  why  the  life  of  Domenico  Savio  should  be
              considered particularly appropriate at the present day, and also why it
              should appeal especially to English Catholics.
                  As will be seen from the narrative which follows, the boyhood
              of Domenico to some extent coincided with that of our present Holy
              Father,—there were less than seven years between the times of their]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO



          birth,—and  in  many  respects  the  early  years  of  the  one  were  like
          those of the other.
              Both were sons of humble peasant families in the North of Italy;
          both  as  boys  had  to  trudge  many  miles  barefooted  day  by  day  to
          attend school; both were distinguished by identical qualities of mind
          and soul.
              More than this. The boy Giuseppe Sarto of Riese was destined
          to become "the Pope of the Eucharist," and no acts of his wonderful
          Pontificate have more profoundly influenced the spiritual life of the
          Catholic Church than his legislation on daily Communion and on the
          first Communion of children on arriving at the use of reason.
              Now  it  is  a  remarkable  fact  that  the  childhood  of  Domenico
          Savio anticipated these profound reforms, inasmuch as, owing to his
          extraordinary sanctity, he was as early as  1849 admitted to his first
          Communion at the age  of seven, and continued thereafter to be a
          daily Communicant.
              At  that  date  such  an  event  must  indeed  have  appeared
          phenomenal  and  seems  to  constitute  Domenico  a  most  suitable
          patron for the juvenile first communicants and daily communicants
          of the present discipline.
              Nor is this all. Domenico Savio, whom we all hope to see one
          day raised to the Altars of the Church, died as a schoolboy and when
          not yet fifteen years of age. He was not a Religious of any Order, he
          was not a Cleric, nor even as yet a church student, though hoping
          one day to become one; he was just an ordinary schoolboy, fond of
          his  games, as  well as of his books. Herein again we seem to see  a
          peculiarly  appropriate  patron  for  all  Catholic  school  children,  for
          Domenico may be truly said to be one of themselves, and in these
          days of educational strife and danger such a patron is more than ever
          needed by our Catholic schools.
              Last of all we cannot but be struck by the extraordinary fact of
          Domenico's interest in England, as mentioned in chapter ten, and his
          wonderful vision narrated in chapter nineteen. As far as I know, there
          is nothing to show why this little Italian schoolboy should have felt
          any interest in England, or indeed how he came to know anything
          about it. It reminds one of the case of St. Paul of the Cross, except
          that it is a much more wonderful phenomenon in the case of a mere
          child.  For  this  reason  I  feel  specially  pleased  to  see  the  life  in  an
          English dress, and I sincerely trust that the book may have a wide


                                         viii]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO


              circulation  in  English  speaking  countries,  and  that  all  readers,  and
              specially the children of our schools, may join in earnest prayer for
              the promotion of the cause of one whom we may hope some day to
              acclaim as "the Schoolboy Saint."


                                                         ✠ LOUIS CHARLES,⁠
                                                              Bishop of Salford.

              St. Bede's College,
              May 6th, 1914.






























                                              ix]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[THE AUTHOR'S PREFACE.

          T
                 he reference made by His Lordship the Bishop of Salford to
                 the Ven. Don Bosco in the preceding preface, convinces us
                 that the introduction to this work, as written by the Servant
          of God, ought not to be omitted from the translation. In fact, all that
          has been written by the Ven. Don Bosco in now regarded as invested
          with  a  higher  authority,  apart  from  its  own  intrinsic  merit,  arising
          from his considerable repute as an author.
              The Ven. Don Bosco addressed these words to the boys of his
          Oratory at Turin:
              You  have  frequently  asked  me  to  write  something  about  your
          former  companion,  Dominic  Savio;  and  now  I  have  done  what  I
          could  to  satisfy  your  desire.  Here  is  his  life,  described  with  that
          brevity and simplicity which I know is most acceptable to you.
              There were two difficulties in the way of publishing this work;
          first there was the criticism to which one is exposed, who describes
          what was performed under the eyes of many witnesses. I think I have
          overcome  this  by  determining  to  narrate  only  what  has  been
          observed by you or by myself, and which I keep preserved in your
          own writing.
              The other obstacle was the necessity of often mentioning myself,
          for as Dominic was three years in this House, I must necessarily refer
          to things with which I am personally connected. This I think I have
          overcome by adhering strictly to the duty of an historian, which is to
          present the statement of facts, irrespective of the persons concerned.
          But if, here and there, I should appear to speak too openly of myself,]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO


              you must put it down to my regard for the boy who has gone, and for
              all of you besides; for this affection makes me open my heart to you,
              as a father does when speaking to his children.
                  Some  of  you  may  wonder  why  I  have  prepared  a  Life  of
              Dominic Savio, and not of other youths who were here at school,
              and  lived  lives  of  eminent  virtue.  It  is  quite  true  that  Divine
              Providence deigned to send us several boys who were examples of
              holiness, such as Gabriel Fascio, Louis Rua, Camillus Gavio, John Massiglia
              and  others;  but  the  incidents  connected  with  these  are  not  so
              conspicuous and remarkable as those of Savio, whose whole life was
              wonderful. However, if God gives me health and grace, I intend to
              publish  a  collection  of  facts  concerning  these  other  companions,
              both to satisfy your desires and my own, and so that you may imitate
              what  may  be  compatible  with  your  state.  In  this  edition  I  have
              inserted  several  new  accounts,  which  will  increase  the  interest  of
              those who have read the former editions.
                  But I would ask you to try to draw profit from what I am going
              to  describe;  say  with  St.  Augustine:  si  illi,  cur  non  ego?  If  a
              companion  of  mine,  of  my  age  and  circumstances,  exposed  to  the
              same or even greater difficulties, could yet remain a faithful disciple
              of Christ, why cannot I do the same? Remember that true religion is
              not  a  matter  of  words;  there  must  be  deeds.  Hence,  if  you  find
              something  related  worthy  of  admiration,  do  not  be  satisfied  with
              saying: I like that, or that is very good; but rather say: I want to put into
              practice what I see is praiseworthy in others.
                  May God grant you, and all the readers of this book, strength
              and  grace  to  draw  profit  from  what  is  therein  contained;  and  may
              Our Blessed Lady, to whom Domenic was so devout, obtain for us
              all one heart and mind in serving God, who alone is worthy of being
              loved above all things, and faithfully served during our whole life.











                                              xi]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[CHAPTER I
                EARLY LIFE AND THE SIGNS OF EXTRAORDINARY
                                           GIFTS.

              A
                      BOUT ten miles from Turin, in the north of Italy, lies the
                      village  of  Castelnuovo  d'Asti,  and  there  in  1841  lived  a
                      good,  hardworking  couple,  Charles  and  Bridget  Savio.
              About  that  time,  however,  there  was  scarcity  of  labour  in  the
              neighbourhood, and they accordingly moved away in the direction of
              Chieri,  which  is  about  nine  miles  south-east  of  Turin;  and,  having
              settled at the little township of Riva, Charles Savio applied himself to
              his trade of an ironworker. On April 2nd of the next year, 1842, a
              child was born, who was to prove a blessing and consolation to his
              parents; he was given the name of Dominic at baptism, and though
              no particular importance was attached to the name at the time, the
              boy,  in  later  years,  held  it  in  particular  esteem,  as  there  will  be
              occasion to learn.
                   When the boy was scarcely two years of age, his parents decided
              to  return  to  their  former  neighbourhood,  and  they  settled  at
              Murialdo,  which  is  quite  close to their  early  home  at  Castelnuovo.
              Like devoted parents, the careful upbringing of their boy was their
              chief  solicitude,  and,  considering  his  tender  years,  Dominic  soon
              displayed an excellent disposition, and piety seemed to be part of his
              very  nature.  Morning  and  evening  prayers  at  once  impressed
              themselves on his childish mind, and at four years of age he could
              recite them all quite readily; he was always attentive to his mother's
              wishes,  and  only  left  her  to  say  his  prayers  in  some  quiet  corner,



                                              1]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

          where he was undisturbed.
             In the unreflecting manner, natural to them, children are generally
          a source of worry and disturbance to their mothers; it is the age when
          they must touch and examine and often taste everything they come
          across;  but  Dominic's  parents  testify  that  he  never  gave  the  least
          trouble in this way. He was not only obedient to the smallest point,
          but  ready  for  any  expression  of  a  wish,  and  tried  to  forsee
          opportunities of doing them some little service. He was quite above
          the average in his appreciation for his parents' kindness, and he had
          his own method of expressing it, particularly as his father returned
          from his day's work. He always ran out to meet him, hoped he was
          not  too  tired,  and  promised  to  pray  for  him  in  return  for  all  his
          labours. So saying, he would enter the house, place his father's chair
          ready,  and  attend  to  all  his  wants.  "This  childish  appreciation  and
          thoughtfulness," says his father, "were naturally very welcome to me,
          and as evening drew nigh I began to feel a particular longing to get
          home, to receive and give these marks of affection; for the boy was
          everything to me."
             Day by day the child's piety increased, and from the time that he
          was  four  years  of  age,  there  was  no  need  to  remind  him  of  his
          prayers, whether morning or evening or at meals, or at the time of
          the Angelus; in fact he would even remind others, should they appear
          to  forget  them.  One  day  some  distraction  occurred  as  they  were
          sitting  down  to  dinner,  and  grace  before  meals  was  forgotten;  but
          little Dominic was too attentive: "Father," he said, "We have not yet
          asked God's blessing on our food," and he straightway made the Sign
          of the Cross and began the usual prayer.
             At another time a stranger was staying in the house, and he sat
          down to his meal without any act of religion. Dominic did not like to
          speak of it openly, yet he was too much moved to remain at the table,
          and went to one of his quiet corners. When he was questioned about
          this  unusual  proceeding  by  his  parents,  he  replied:  "I  could  not
          remain at table with one who eats as do the beasts without a thought
          of God."












                                          2]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[CHAPTER II
                EXAMPLES OF YOUTHFUL VIRTUE AT MURIALDO.
                             HIS EARLY DAYS AT SCHOOL.

              I
                   T is a common thing to find people who are incredulous on the
                   subject of youthful piety, and therefore it would be well to state
                   at  the  outset  that,  for  the  following  account,  the  writer  is
              drawing directly from the narrative of the parish priest of the district
              in which Murialdo lay. In his written account he states:
                 "Soon  after  I  had  been  appointed  to  Murialdo,  and  had
              commenced my duties, my notice was drawn in a special manner to a
              little boy of about five years of age who was brought by his mother
              to  the  church.  His  gentle  countenance,  his  air  of  composure,  his
              whole  demeanour  so  devout  and  attractive,  drew  my  attention  to
              him, as they had already drawn the notice of others. When he had
              learnt the way to church, he would sometimes arrive there before the
              doors were opened; however, it did not suggest itself to him to spend
              the interval in play, as doubtless other boys would have done, but he
              used  to  kneel  down  on  the  steps,  place  himself  in  an  attitude  of
              prayer and remain thus till the church was opened. Neither rain nor
              snow seemed to affect him in any way when he was thus occupied. It
              was  therefore  very  natural  that  I  should  be  curious  to  make  the
              acquaintance  of  this  extraordinary  child,  and  I  found  that  he  was
              none other than the little son of the blacksmith, Charles Savio.
                 If he ever saw me in the street he immediately made a respectful
              and joyful salutation, and always anticipated my greeting. It was about
              this  time  that  he  commenced  to  attend  the  parish  school,  and  his


                                              3]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

          already  acquired  habits  of  diligence  and  of  taking  pains  with
          everything, soon showed their effect in his rapid progress. He had, of
          course, to mix with the young and thoughtless boys of his own age,
          but  he  always  managed  to  avoid  their  little  quarrels  and  disputes,
          although this at times brought upon him taunts and insults, which he
          bore with remarkable courage and patience. The usual boyish, but by
          no means praiseworthy, tricks and escapades were part of the usual
          programme of his companions, but Dominic generally found means
          for being otherwise employed when these were in progress.
             The  little  habits  of  piety  already  described  increased  with  the
          growing years of his boyhood, and developed in proportion as he had
          scope for its practice. At five years of age he had already learnt to
          serve Mass and did so with great devotion. He went in good time
          every  day  to  the  church,  and,  dearly  as  he  loved  to  serve,  he  was
          ready to yield the privilege to others if they wished to do so, in which
          case he assisted with great devotion. He often went to Confession,
          and as soon as he was allowed to make his First Communion he did
          so with fervour and delight. At the sight of so many signs of unusual
          piety I often used to think to myself: "Here surely is a boy of great
          promise; God grant that some means  may be found to bring  such
          rare gifts to maturity." … Such was the narrative of the parish priest
          of Murialdo, who had watched over the childhood of this gifted boy.
































                                          4]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[CHAPTER III
                     DOMINIC IS ALLOWED TO MAKE HIS FIRST
                      COMMUNION BEFORE THE USUAL AGE.
                     PREPARATION FOR THE IMPORTANT DAY.
                                   HIS RESOLUTIONS.

              I
                   T was remarked in the foregoing chapter that Dominic showed
                   exceptional  piety  when  he  approached  the  Holy  Table,  but
                   there  were  important  circumstances  connected  with  his  First
              Communion  that  call  for  consideration.  As  far  as  dispositions  are
              concerned,  Dominic  appeared  to have  the  most  excellent ones; he
              knew the necessary catechism thoroughly; he had a clear knowledge,
              considering  his  years,  of  this  the  greatest  of  the  Sacraments,  and
              moreover, his desire to receive it was eager and constant. The only
              obstacle, therefore, was his age, for at that time, children were usually
              not allowed to make their First Communion before they were eleven
              or twelve. Savio was only a boy of seven, and he hardly looked his
              few  years,  so  that  the  parish  priest  hesitated.  He  consulted  the
              neighbouring  priests,  and  having  carefully  considered  the  boy's
              knowledge  and  dispositions,  all  doubt  and  hesitation  were  finally
              swept aside, and Dominic was allowed to partake, for the first time,
              of the food of angels.
                 The boy could not repress his delight when he was told this good
              news, and a supernatural joy seemed to take possession of his soul.
              He ran to his mother to tell her; he was eager to spend more time in
              prayer, or in reading the instructions for Holy Communion; he spent
              more time than ever at church, before and after Mass; he seemed to



                                              5]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

          be already communing with the angels in adoration. On the eve of
          the great event in his life, he said to his mother: "As I am going to
          make my First Communion tomorrow, forgive me the pain I have
          caused you in the past; from now I shall be much better; I shall be
          more attentive at school, and more obedient in whatever you tell me
          to  do."  His  sorrow  for  what  he  imagined  to  be  his  past  faults  so
          moved  him  as  to  fill  his  eyes  with  tears;  and  the  mother,  deeply
          touched, as was natural, at these pious dispositions in her boy, and
          remembering  that  in  the  past  he  had  been  a  continual  source  of
          consolation to her, comforted him by saying: "Put your fears away,
          my child, whatever you may have done is all forgiven; pray that God
          may keep you good, and pray for your father and mother."
             When that memorable day dawned, he rose early, and long before
          the time set off for the church, which he found still shut. He knelt
          down on the step, as was his wont, and said his prayers till the doors
          were opened to admit the children, who by this time had gathered
          together.  There  were  still  some  confessions  to  be  heard,  so  that,
          allowing  for  preparation  and  thanksgiving,  and  the  Mass  and
          discourse,  the  function  of  the  First  Communion  was  a  matter  of
          hours. Dominic had been the first to arrive to offer his salutation to
          God;  he  was  the  last  to  retire  after  his  thanksgiving.  The  whole
          period had been for him one of abstraction from things of earth, and
          of contact with the things of heaven.
             Later on, when any reference was made to his First Communion
          day,  his  face  would  light  up  with  joy,  as  he  exclaimed:  "That  was
          indeed a day of happy remembrances for me." It was a sort of re-
          commencement of a life which might serve as a model to all. In his
          little  book of  devotions  he  wrote  down  some  resolutions,  which  I
          have  been  able  to  transcribe  with  all  their  original  and  direct
          simplicity, and their introduction in diary form:
             "Resolutions made by me, Dominic Savio, in the year 1849, on the
          day of my First Communion, at the age of seven.

             1.  I  will  go  to  Confession  often,  and  as  frequently  to  Holy
          Communion as my confessor allows.
             2. I wish to sanctify the Sundays and festivals in a special manner.
             3. My friends shall be Jesus and Mary.
             4. Death rather than sin.




                                          6]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO

                 These  resolutions  were  not  simply  written  out  and  then  put
              carefully away; he read them very often, and they were a guide to him
              throughout his life.
                 If among the readers of this little work there should chance to be
              some who are yet to make their First Communion, I would strongly
              urge  them to follow young  Savio as  their model. But in particular,
              fathers and mothers, and those who exercise any authority over the
              young, should attach the greatest importance to this religious act; for
              a  First  Communion  that  is  well  made  constitutes  a  solid  moral
              foundation  for  the  whole  future  life;  and  it  would  be  indeed
              surprising if this solemn act, when worthily performed, did not result
              in a virtuous life.
                 On the other hand, great numbers of young people are met with,
              who  are  the  despair  of  their  parents  and  of  those  who  interest
              themselves in them; the root of this evil is generally found to lie in
              the fact, that their preparation for First Communion was carelessly
              conducted, or in great part neglected. It would be better to delay it, or
              even not to make it at all, than that it should be made badly.






































                                              7]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[CHAPTER IV
             DOMINIC'S SCHOOL CAREER AT CASTELNUOVO
          D'ASTI. TRIALS AND DIFFICULTIES. HIS TREATMENT
              OF EVIL COUNSEL. HIS MASTER'S ENCOMIUM.

          A
                  S  his  early  studies  were  now  completed,  Dominic  should
                  have been sent away to a higher school for more advanced
                  classes, which a small country place could not provide. He
          was very desirous that this should be arranged, and his parents were
          greatly  in  favour  of  it,  but  their  condition  did  not  allow  of  the
          realisation  of  such  ambitious  plans.  Divine  Providence,  however,
          intended to provide the means, so that the boy might attain the end
          appointed for him.
             Dominic had often said in his playful manner: "If I were a bird I
          should like to fly every morning to Castelnuovo d'Asti so as to go on
          with my studies."
             His  eager desire to continue his  studies made him overcome all
          difficulties, and it was arranged that he should attend the Municipal
          schools, although they were two miles away from his home. He had
          to walk there and back; he was not yet ten years of age, and all the
          variations of weather, both for summer and winter, had to be put up
          with; but all difficulties were to be overcome; Dominic was satisfied
          that he was thus performing an act of obedience to his parents which
          meant advancing in the science of the Saints, and this appeared to
          him more than enough reason for putting up with any inconvenience.
             One  day  an  elderly  person  saw  Dominic  going  along  the  road,
          about  two  o'clock  in  the  afternoon,  under  a  broiling  sun,  and,
          meaning to give him a little encouragement, said to him: "Are you



                                          8]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO

              not afraid to go so far alone?"
                 "I am not alone," said Dominic, "I have my angel guardian with
              me, accompanying every step."
                 "But surely you find the journey long and tiresome in this very hot
              weather."
                 "Nothing seems tiresome or painful when you are working for a
              master who pays well."
                 "And who is your master?"
                 "It is  God, our Creator, who rewards even a cup of cold water
              given for love of Him."
                 This  little  incident  was  related  by  the  person  who  had  the
              conversation with Dominic, and he concludes by saying: "A boy who
              has  such  thoughts  in  his  head,  when  he  is  only  ten  years  old,  is
              certainly destined for some great career."
                 At  school  Dominic  soon  found  how  to  distinguish  between
              desirable  companions  and  those  whose  influence  was  bad.  If  he
              noticed one who was diligent and respectful, who knew his lessons
              well, and always worked hard, Dominic sought his companionship;
              an  unruly,  insolent  boy,  or  one  who  neglected  his  work,  he  left
              severely  alone. He  was  always  kindly  in  his  manner towards  them,
              and seized any opportunity of doing them a litle service, but he took
              care not to become intimate with them.
                 His  conduct  at  the  higher  school  of  Castelnuovo  d'Asti  might
              serve  as  a  model  to  any  young  student  who  desires  to  advance  in
              knowledge  and  virtue.  For  this  reason,  the  account  given  by  his
              master is useful and noteworthy. He says:
                 "I very willingly send you an account of Dominic Savio, because
              in  a  very  short  time  he  gained  a  high  place  in  my  estimation  and
              affection, and because I still have a vivid recollection of his excellent
              behaviour, his zeal in good works and his many virtues. I cannot say
              much about the performance of his religious duties, for he attended
              the parish church of his own district, which was two or three miles
              from  the  school;  for  that  reason  he  did  not  belong  to  our
              confraternity,  though  he  was  just  the  sort  of  boy  we  should  have
              been glad to admit.
                 He came to this school as soon as his elementary course was over,
              beginning on the feast of St. Aloysius, June 21st, 1852. That was, in
              itself,  a  little  extraordinary,  for  the  great  patron of  young  students
              found  no  more  devoted  follower  than  Dominic.  He  was  gentle  in



                                              9]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

          appearance and manner, and had an air about him of mingled gravity
          and  affability.  His  disposition  was  always  marked  by  calmness  and
          good nature; both in school and out of it, his conduct was such as to
          produce a most agreeable impression, and for me to deal with him in
          the course of his school work was like a reward for the many fatigues
          so often to be endured in the training of boys, who are often dull and
          not  eager  for  lessons. Hence  it  may  very  well  be  said  that  he  was
          Savio (wise), not only in name, but in fact, viz., in his studies, in piety,
          in conversation and his dealing with others, and in all his actions.
             From the day he entered the school to the end of that scholastic
          year, and during the four months of the next year that he spent with
          us,  his  progress  in  his  studies  was  little  short  of  phenomenal.  He
          speedily gained the first place in his class, and the other honours of
          the school, and invariably got full marks for the subjects which were
          examined from time to time. These eminently successful results must
          be attributed to his exceptional abilities and to his love of study and
          virtue.
             Deserving also of special praise was his exactness in every duty, no
          matter how trivial, and his constant attendance at the classes, in spite
          of all difficulties and of his long walk to the school. He was by no
          means a robust or vigorous boy, and this going to and from school, a
          distance  of  nearly  three  miles  each  way,  would  in  itself  be  ample
          proof of his assiduity in his studies. But during that year, 1852–1853,
          he showed signs of weakness and general failing health, so that his
          parents decided on a change of abode. I was disappointed at losing so
          promising  a  pupil,  to  whom  I  had  become  attached,  but  I  had
          expected to lose him, for I had seen that his delicate constitution was
          beginning to give way under the strain; and when I heard later on that
          he was to go to the Oratory at Turin, I was quite satisfied, as I knew
          he would there have the opportunity for the cultivation of his rare
          intellect and piety."
             Such is the account given by the master of his class.















                                         10]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[CHAPTER V
                   DOMINIC'S SCHOOL-LIFE AT MONDONIO. HIS
                    CONDUCT UNDER A CALUMNIOUS CHARGE.

              I
                   T would seem that Divine Providence had designed to make it
                   clear to Dominic that this world is truly a land of exile, where,
                   like pilgrims, we are always moving  from place to place; or it
              may have been that it was in order to make him known in several
              districts, that his virtues might be displayed in each.
                 As has been mentioned, it was towards the close of the year 1852
              that  Dominic's  parents  found  that  their  boy's  health  would
              necessitate  another  change  of  abode,  and  this  time  they  went  to
              Mondonio, a village not far away from Castelnuovo. Here again we
              find that nothing but the most edifying reports are given of Dominic.
              It will not be necessary to quote a full account given by his master at
              Mondonio, for it repeats the good points mentioned by his former
              master at Murialdo. Attention will be drawn only to certain facts of
              particular importance.
                 The priest in question, writes: "I can state, without hesitation, that
              during my twenty years experience with boys never met one to equal
              Savio in frank and genuine piety. He was gifted, too, with a wisdom
              beyond his years; and his diligence, application and affability, made
              him a favourite both with masters and companions. When I noticed
              him in church his recollection was such as to fill me with wonder; his
              manner and attitude suggested the thought: "Here is an innocent soul
              to whom the delights of heaven are opened, and who by his piety
              soars aloft to the company of the angels in Heaven."




                                             11]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

             The following incident is worthy of special record:
             "One day a serious offence had been committed by certain pupils
          of mine, and the guilty ones, when found, were to be expelled. The
          culprits  thought  out  several  expedients  in  order  to  escape  the
          punishment, and at last settled on the plan of accusing Dominic of
          the offence. I very naturally refused entirely to believe that Dominic
          would  be  capable  of  any  such  thing,  but  the  story  and  accusation
          were so skilfully put together, that it had all the semblance of truth
          and conviction.
             When I entered the school in the morning, prepared to deal with
          the matter, I was in an indignant frame of mind, and spoke in general
          terms to the class. Then I turned to Savio and spoke very severely to
          him,  telling  him  that  he  deserved  to  be  expelled,  and  it  was  only
          because it was the first offence he had been guilty of, that he would
          not be sent away; but that if ever the like occurred again, expulsion
          would certainly follow. Dominic might have very easily shown that
          he was entirely innocent, but he made no reply. He hung down his
          head, as one who was deservedly reproved, and made no attempt at
          clearing his character.
             But it is seldom God's way to let the innocent remain under the
          cloud  of  calumny,  and  on  the  very  next  day  the  culprits  were
          discovered. Deeply regretting now the harsh terms of the reproof I
          had made to the boy, I sent for him and said: "Why did you not tell
          me that you had had nothing to do with it?" He replied in his usual
          candid manner: "I knew that the guilty boy was already under threat
          of expulsion for other things, but I hoped to be forgiven, since it was
          the  first  act  of  misconduct  ever  imputed  to  me  at  school.  I  also
          remembered that Our Lord had been unjustly accused."
             At this reply I was silent; I somehow felt that there was nothing
          more to be said; not only the masters, but the whole school admired
          this act of generous resignation to suffering and insult on behalf of
          others, especially at the risk of being humiliated and disgraced.















                                         12]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[CHAPTER VI
                 MY FIRST MEETING WITH DOMINIC SAVIO. SOME
                    CURIOUS INCIDENTS CONNECTED WITH IT.

              T
                     HE matter contained in the following chapters is based upon
                     more  personal  and  complete  evidence,  for  almost  all  the
                     incidents  occurred  under  my  own  notice,  and  also  in  the
              presence  of  a  large  number  of  boys  who  are  unanimous  in  their
              attestation of them.
                 It  was  in  1854  that  Fr.  Cugliero,  the  priest  who  relates  the
              incidents mentioned in the foregoing chapter, came to see me about a
              pupil of his. "Here in your Oratory," he said, "there might possibly be
              boys equal to him, but I can safely assert that there is none to excel
              him; in fact you will find him to be another St. Aloysius."
                 At that time I used to take my boys occasionally to Murialdo. It
              was  a  little  country  place,  where  a  short  time  was  spent  for  the
              benefit of enjoying the country air and open life; and there we usually
              made the Novena in preparation for, and celebrated the Feast of the
              Holy  Rosary.  It  was  accordingly  arranged  that  while  I  was  at
              Murialdo, Dominic should be brought over from Mondonio to see
              me.
                 It  was  therefore  at  Murialdo,  on  the  first  Monday  in  October
              1864,  that  I  became  acquainted  with  Dominic  Savio.  He  was
              accompanied by his father, and as they came up to speak to me, I
              noticed  his  pleasant,  but  respectful  manner,  and  something  in  his
              demeanour fixed my attention upon him. When he came up I put a
              question to him, to which he answered: "I am the boy of whom Fr.



                                             13]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

          Cugliero  has  spoken  to  you.  I  have  come  with  my  father  from
          Mondonio.
             We walked together and I questioned him about his studies, and
          his  desires  for  the  future,  and  we  were  immediately  on  the  most
          friendly and confidential terms. I may say that I at once recognised a
          boy after God's own heart, and I could not help being struck by the
          workings of grace, already manifest in one of such tender years.
             After some minutes conversation, and before I could turn aside to
          speak to his father, he said to me: "Well, what do you think of the
          matter; will you take me to Turin to study?" I replied that I thought
          there was very good material to work upon. "And what do you think
          you can make of it?" Seeing that he fully grasped my meaning I said:
          "Something beautiful and acceptable to God." To this he replied:
             "Then I must be the material and you are to fashion it; take me
          with  you  therefore."  "But,"  I  said,  "I  am  afraid  that  your  delicate
          health would not stand the strain of much study." "I don't think we
          need fear on that point," he said. "God has given me health and every
          assistance till now, and He will surely help me in the future." I then
          asked him what he thought of doing when his preliminary course was
          finished. To this he replied: "If I could hope for such a favour from
          God,  I  ardently  desire  to  become  a  priest."  "Very  well,"  I  replied;
          "now I want to see whether you are able to learn quickly; take this
          little book and study this page of it; tomorrow I shall see if you know
          it."
             I then sent him to see the other boys and to join in their games,
          while I talked to his father. But a little surprise awaited me, for hardly
          ten minutes had elapsed when Dominic came back, and said with his
          usual  pleasant  manner:  "If  you  like,  I  will  recite  that  page  to  you
          now." I took the book in some astonishment, and this only increased
          when he recited the page by heart, and could explain any passage in
          it. "Well done," I said, "as you have anticipated your lesson, I shall
          anticipate my answer. I will take you to Turin and you will be one of
          my chosen boys; you must now pray that God will help both you and
          me to do His Holy Will."
             Not knowing how to express his great gratitude he took my hand,
          and  said:  "I  hope  my  behaviour  will  never  give  you  cause  for
          complaint."






                                         14]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[CHAPTER VII
                       DOMINIC COMES TO THE ORATORY OF
                   ST. FRANCIS OF SALES. HIS MANNER OF LIFE.

              N
                       OTHING is more characteristic of youth than its tendency
                       to changeableness. A decision is taken on a certain thing to-
                       day, tomorrow all will be changed; there may be virtue in a
              heroic degree one day, but on the next the opposite may manifest
              itself;  and  this  is  where  there  is  need of  guidance  and  firmness  in
              education,  lest  unhappy  results  should  follow.  There  was  no  sign
              whatever of this in Dominic. All the virtues seemed to grow together
              in him and he was able to practice them all in combination.
                 Directly he came to the Oratory, he came to my room, in order to
              place himself, as he said, entirely in the hands of his Director. He at
              once caught sight of an inscription which bore the favourite words of
              St. Francis of Sales: "Da mihi animas, caetera tolle." He began to read
              it attentively, and I desired him to grasp the meaning. So I helped
              him to make it out, the translation being: "Give me souls; take away
              everything else!" He seemed to reflect a moment, and then he said: "I
              think I understand; here the aim is not to gain money, but to win
              souls, and I hope that my soul will be included in the number."
                 His mode of life was just the routine life of school-work; and at
              first  there  was  nothing  extraordinary  to  remark,  beyond  his
              scrupulous observance of every rule. At study or any other duty, he
              was at once diligent and zealous. Convinced that the Word of God is
              the guide to Heaven, he was particularly attentive to instructions and
              sermons, and from them he gathered maxims and rules of conduct



                                             15]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

          which formed his constant guide.
             He always made a point of asking for explanations of difficulties,
          and  thus  he  was  able to  make  continual progress  in  virtue,  and  in
          exactness  in  the  performance  of  his  duties,  so  that  it  would  be
          difficult  to  go  beyond  the  excellence  he  attained.  He  had  already
          requested  the  favour  of  having  his  faults  pointed  out,  so  that  his
          conduct towards all became equally praiseworthy; he was very apt at
          noticing what should be avoided in the conduct of a companion, and
          what  should  be  imitated,  and  Dominic  chose  his  companions
          accordingly.
             The  year  1854  was  drawing  rapidly  to  its  close.  It  was  a
          memorable year throughout the Catholic World, for all were awaiting
          the declaration of the Dogma of the Immaculate Conception. We, at
          the  Oratory,  were  preparing  to  celebrate  the  occasion  with  due
          solemnity, and endeavouring to draw some spiritual advantage from
          it.
             Savio was one of those who felt a desire to celebrate the great day
          in the manner most acceptable to Our Lady. He wrote out on nine
          pieces  of  paper  an  act  of  virtue  to  be  practised  every  day  of  the
          Novena,  drawing  out  one  each  day.  These  he  faithfully  put  into
          practice, and approached the Sacraments with great devotion. On the
          evening  of  December  8th,  Dominic  knelt  before  the Altar  of  Our
          Lady, and, with the approval of his Confessor, renewed the promises
          made at his First Communion, begging particularly that he might be
          faithful to the last of the four, repeating his  petition several times.
          Strengthened  thus  in  fervour  by  his  recourse  to  the  Immaculate
          Mother of God, his conduct appeared so edifying, and included such
          acts of virtue, that I began to note them down so as not to let them
          be forgotten.
             Coming now to describe the particular doings of the boy I find
          that  I  am  confronted  with  quite  an  array  of  events  and  virtuous
          actions  deserving  of  mention.  For  the  sake  of  greater  clearness  I
          propose  to  group  together  certain  incidents  which  deal  with  one
          phase  or  one  particular  matter,  rather  than  to  adhere  to  a  strict
          chronological sequence.










                                         16]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[CHAPTER VIII
                HIS STUDIES AT THE ORATORY. HIS CONDUCT AT
                  SCHOOL. HIS DEALINGS WITH QUARRELS AND
                                   SPECIAL DANGERS.

              H
                        AVING already laid a good foundation at Mondonio for
                        the study of Latin, and owing to his powers of application
                        and  exceptional  talent,  Dominic  was  soon  raised  to  the
              fourth  class,  which,  according  to  present  scholastic  arrangements,
              would correspond to the second course  of Latin grammar. During
              this course he was one of the pupils of Professor Bonzanino, for at
              that time classes for students were not yet conducted at the Oratory
              itself. Were I to speak here of his conduct, of the advancement he
              made, of his exemplary behaviour, I should have to repeat what his
              previous  masters  said  of  him.  I  shall  therefore  restrict  myself  to
              relating some incidents which were noted down during this period by
              those who were closely associated with him. The Professor himself
              often said that he could not recollect ever having had a pupil more
              attentive, more respectful than young Savio, for he was quite a model
              in everything. There was never any affectation about his manner or
              appearance;  he  was  always  careful  and  courteous,  so  that  his
              companions, many of whom were drawn from good families, were
              anxious  to  become  friendly  and  to  converse  with  him.  If  the
              professor  noticed  a  pupil  who  was  restless  and  troublesome,  he
              contrived to put him near Dominic, who, in his own tactful way, was
              sure to get him to keep silence, and apply himself to study or the
              work then in hand.



                                             17]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

             It is during this year that the record of Dominic's life gives us an
          incident full of heroism, and which is the more remarkable when his
          youth is taken into consideration, for he was only fourteen when he
          came to the Oratory. The occurrence in question concerns two of his
          school-fellows, between whom a fierce quarrel had arisen, on account
          of some remarks on a point of family honour. The quarrel proceeded
          from  the  exchanging  of  insults  to  the  giving  of  blows  and  stone-
          throwing.  Dominic  came  to  hear  of  this  quarrel,  but  he  saw  the
          difficulty of trying to interfere, for both boys were older and bigger
          than he was. However he found means for approaching each in turn,
          urged them to give up their hatred, and pointed out that anger and
          revenge were against the commandments of God; he wrote to each
          of them, threatening to acquaint their parents and their master, but
          the  headstrong  boys  were  not  to  be  influenced;  their  minds  had
          become so embittered that all entreaties were in vain. Apart from the
          risk  of  bodily  injury  to  themselves,  Dominic  was  most  concerned
          with the offence against God, and he was eager to find some means
          of  effectually  interfering,  but  was  perplexed  as  to  the  manner  of
          doing so.
             He then seemed to have an inspiration. He waited for the boys
          after school, and contriving to speak to each alone, he said: "Since
          you will persist in this insane and sinful quarrel I ask you to accept
          one condition." Each agreed, provided it did not interfere with their
          challenge  of  a  fight  with  stones,  and  indulged  in  some  very
          unbecoming language in reference to his enemy. The very language
          was  enough  to  make  Savio  shudder,  but  desirous  of  preventing  a
          greater  evil  he  said:  "The  condition  I  wish  to  impose  does  not
          interfere with the challenge." "Then what is it?" "I shall not tell you
          till you meet for the duel."
             They  thought  he  was  making  game  of  them,  but  Savio  insisted
          that he was quite serious and that he would be on the scene. Neither
          could conjecture what his plan was.
             The place for the fight was a lonely spot outside the town. The
          boys, getting more and more incensed, were almost going to fight on
          the way, but Dominic managed to prevent them. The scene of action
          was reached, and the boys took up their positions at a little distance
          from each other, and had by them the stones they were to hurl. Now
          was  Dominic's  time  for  mediation.  He  stepped  in  the  middle  and
          said: "Before you commence to fight you must fulfil the condition



                                         18]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO

              you agreed upon." So saying he drew out of his coat-pocket a crucifix
              and held it up in the air. "I desire," he said, "that each of you should
              look on this crucifix, and then if you will throw, you must throw the
              stone  at  me  and  say:  Our  Saviour  died  pardoning  his  very
              persecutioners; I, a sinner, am about to offend Him by an act of open
              revenge."
                 Having  said this, he threw himself on his knees  before the one
              who seemed most enraged, and said: "Throw your stone at me; let
              me have the first blow." A shiver seemed to go through the boy thus
              addressed. "No," he exclaimed, "I couldn't do it. I am not so mean as
              that. I have nothing against you."
                 On hearing this Dominic turned to the other boy, who had been
              watching in amazement, and made the same proposal to him. He too
              refused such a cowardly act.
                 Then Dominic got up and said, with great earnestness: "You are
              both ashamed to commit this act of brutality against me, and yet you
              would commit it against God and lose your soul by grievous  sin."
              And he held up the crucifix again.
                 This proved too much for the two boys; they were moved by his
              true Christian charity and his courage. One of them confessed that he
              felt a cold shiver, and felt thoroughly ashamed that he had forced a
              friend of Savio's character to take such extreme measures. Wishing to
              make him some amends, he forgave entirely the boy with whom he
              had  quarreled  and  promised  to  go  to  Confession  at  once.  Thus
              Dominic secured a victory for charity and taught the boys a lesson. Is
              it too striking an act of courage to recommend for example to young
              school-boys? This incident would have remained a profound secret,
              had it not been related by both boys who were the partners to the
              challenge.
                 It  will  be  gathered  from  this  incident  that  Dominic  had  gained
              great influence over his companions, but he often had to put up with
              annoyance  from  some  who  tried  to  draw  him  into  undesirable
              practices. On one occasion in fact he had almost consented to go off
              with  some  boys,  who  wished  him  to  join  them  at  play  instead  of
              going to school, but the arguments against it arose so vividly before
              him, that he not only rejected the proposal for himself, but convinced
              the others that it would be wrong, and made them go with him to
              school.




                                             19]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

             At the end of that year he was among the very best of those who
          were promoted to a higher class, but when his next year began there
          were already signs that his health would need careful attention, and it
          was thought more prudent to let him have some private teaching at
          the Oratory, where intervals of rest and fewer tasks could be given
          him. Under this arrangement his health seemed to improve a good
          deal, so that he was again sent out to the higher classes in the town,
          this time to Professor Picco, who was held in the highest estimation
          as  a  teacher.  Several  interesting  facts  are  recorded  of  this  year  of
          rhetoric,  and  they  will  be  related  in  their  turn  as  the  narrative
          proceeds.


















































                                         20]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[CHAPTER IX
                DOMINIC FORMS THE RESOLUTION OF STRIVING
                                  AFTER PERFECTION.

              I
                   N the above chapters we have considered Dominic as a student
                   going through his scholastic course, and have insisted principally
                   on  his  talents  and  industry.  His  spiritual  advancement  was  of
              even greater importance in his eyes. Savio had been at the Oratory
              for six months when he heard a sermon delivered there on an easy
              method  of  arriving  at  the  perfection  of  the  saints.  The  preacher
              brought out particularly these three points that impressed themselves
              deeply on Savio's mind: first, that it was God's will that we should
              become perfect; secondly, that it was easy to become so; thirdly, that
              an  exceeding  great  reward  is  laid  up  for  those  who  arrive  at
              perfection. The effect of the sermon on Dominic was to set his heart
              aglow with love of God. For some days he was extraordinarily quiet,
              so that his companions began to remark it, and I noticed it myself. I
              began to think that his health was commencing to give way again, so
              I questioned him about it.
                 His  answer  was  put  very  quaintly:  "If  I  am  suffering  at  all,"  he
              said,  "it  is  from  something  beneficial."  I  asked  him  to  explain:  he
              replied that he had been thinking  over the sermon and was  seized
              with  the  desire  of  becoming  a  saint;  that  it  now  appeared  to  him
              much  easier  than  he  had  thought,  and  asked  for  some  special
              guidance in regard to his behaviour. I very naturally praised his good
              intentions, but pointed out that it would not be beneficial for him to
              be  disturbed  and  uneasy  about  it,  for  in  such  disquiet  of  soul  the



                                             21]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

          voice of God could not be heard. I told him he should be always
          happy and cheerful, to be exact in the practices of piety and his other
          duties, and to take his recreation regularly with his companions.
             One day I told him I wished to make him a little present, but that
          I  left  the  choice  of  it  to  him.  "I  do  not  desire  anything  else,"  he
          replied, "but to become perfect; if I do not obtain that I shall be fit
          for nothing." On another occasion we were discussing the etymology
          of  names,  and  he  put  the  question:  "What  does  Dominic  mean?"
          Some one answered: "Belonging to God." "See then," he promptly
          replied, "if I was not right in saying that I ought to become a saint;
          even my very name says that I belong to God; therefore it shall be my
          constant endeavour to become a saint."
             These  and  similar  words  on  other  occasions  may  seem
          extraordinary  in  so  young  a  boy,  but  Dominic  meant  them  in  all
          seriousness; and his use of them, just referred to, was not because he
          was  not leading  a holy life; on the contrary; but it was  because he
          wished to undertake penances, and remain for hours in prayer, things
          which his superiors decided were not suitable for his years or health,
          or his occupations.





































                                         22]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[CHAPTER X
                       ZEAL FOR THE SALVATION OF SOULS.


              T
                     HE chief recommendation given to Dominic, to help him to
                     attain perfection, was to endeavour to gain souls to God, for
                     no  action  is  more  meritorious  than  to  co-operate  in  the
              salvation of souls, for which Our Divine Saviour shed His Precious
              Blood. Dominic had a particular intuition of the importance of this
              good work, and on several occasions he said: "If I could help to gain
              my companions to God, what a happiness it would be!" It was on
              this principle that he never let any occasion go by of doing something
              to  this  end,  and  accordingly  he  frequently  gave  friendly  advice  or
              warning to those of the boys whose conduct was not approved of.
                 He had a particular horror of anything in the nature of blasphemy
              or taking the name of God in vain; in fact, it worked upon him to
              such a degree that his health was quite affected by it. If he heard any
              words of that nature, as he passed along the streets, he would look
              down  as  though  in  sorrow,  and  make  some  pious  ejaculation.  A
              companion had often noticed him raise his cap and utter a few words
              of  prayer  when  these  blasphemies  had  been  uttered.  On  another
              occasion,  as  he  returned  from  school  to the  Oratory,  he  heard  an
              elderly  man  utter  some  very  blasphemous  words.  Dominic
              shuddered,  and  immediately  offered  up  his  pious  ejaculation  in
              reparation. But he was satisfied neither, nor disposed to let it pass.
              Summoning all his courage, and not at all affected by human respect,
              he went up to the man and asked him to direct him to the Oratory.
                                             23]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

          The boy's gentle manner immediately softened the man's anger, and
          he replied, very affably: "No, I am sorry, I don't know where it is."
          "Then there is another favour you can do me," said Dominic. "Oh,
          what is it?" The boy then came nearer and said in a low voice, only
          audible to the man in question: "It would be a great pleasure to me,
          if,  when  you  are  angry  again,  you  would  use  words  that  are  not
          blasphemous."
             The man was naturally astonished at such a request from a boy,
          but  there  was  something  of  admiration  in  his  suprise;  he  replied:
          "Well done, you are right, it is a very bad habit, that I am determined
          to overcome."
             But  Dominic's  manner  with  young  offenders  was  different.  He
          once  heard  two  little  boys  quarrelling  at  their  games  outside  the
          house, and one of them in his boyish anger  used  the Holy Name.
          Dominic  was  pained,  as  he  always  was  when  this  occurred,  so  he
          stepped between the two boys and made them patch up their quarrel.
          Then he turned to the one that he had heard utter the name of God
          and said to him: "Come with me, there is something to be done, with
          which you will be pleased." He took him off to a church, nearby, and
          both went up to the altar. There he made the boy kneel down and ask
          pardon for his profane use of the Holy Name. The boy did not know
          the  act  of  contrition,  so  Dominic  made  him  say  it  after  him,  and
          added  to  it  some  pious  ejaculations,  to  atone  for  the  irreverence
          offered to God.
             Pursuing the same plan, Dominic made himself acquainted chiefly
          with  the  lives  of  those  Saints  who  had  spent  their  lives  in  the
          salvation of souls. A favourite topic with him was the missionary life,
          and what missionaries were actually undertaking at that time; and as it
          was  impossible  for  him  to  help  them  materially,  he  offered  daily
          prayers  for  their  welfare,  and  at  least  one  Communion  a  week.
          Strangely enough I have often heard him exclaim: "How many souls
          there are in England awaiting our assistance; there is nothing would
          please me more, had I the strength and virtue, than to go there and
          help, by preaching and good works, to gain them to Jesus Christ." He
          frequently  lamented  the  lack  of  zeal  in  this  direction,  and  also  as
          regards the proper instruction of children in the truths of the Faith. It
          was his idea, that as soon as he was a cleric, he would go back to
          Mondonio,  gather  the  children  together,  and  teach  them  their

                                         24]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO

              catechism and to lead good lives. And he gave practical proof of this,
              for he often taught catechism in the church of the Oratory, and if any
              boy was backward, or had been neglected in regard to his religion,
              Dominic was always glad to take him in hand to instruct him, and
              prepare him for the Sacraments.
                 This  of  course  could  not  be  carried  on  without  remarks  from
              those who thought his zeal was  out of place, and that such things
              should  only  be  mentioned  in  church.  A  companion  rebuked  him
              once  for  talking  on  the  life  of  some  Saint  in  recreation  time,  and
              asked him why he did so. Dominic's answer was so full of genuine
              zeal for the good of souls, which, he remarked, had been redeemed
              with a great price, that it made a deep impression on those around.
                 During the intervals he spent at home for the holidays, Dominic
              put this zeal of his  into practical effect; for he would gather other
              boys around him - and he had quite a gift for attracting them - and by
              conversations and stories he gave them good instruction and counsel,
              He also took home several objects of piety from the Oratory, and
              distributed  them  judiciously  by  way  of  rewards  among  these
              companions.  It  was  therefore  quite  customary  for  several  to
              accompany him to Mass and the Sacraments, and this good work had
              a lasting effect. During these  holidays he was  brought into contact
              with many people of all ages and conditions, for Dominic's manner
              had an attraction for all; and to all of them, in one way or another, he
              was  the  means  of  some  spiritual  advantage.  No  wonder  that  his
              reputation  began  to  spread,  even  at  that  time.  Dominic's  guiding
              motto was, that no occasion for doing good to souls, or of offering
              some  little  act  of  reparation  to  God,  should  be  missed;  and  this
              accounts  for  his  constant  zeal,  and  his  visits  to  the  Blessed
              Sacrament, in which he generally managed to be accompanied by a
              friend or some one he wished to bring to a better life.














                                             25]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[CHAPTER XI
             VARIOUS INCIDENTS. HIS ATTRACTIVE MANNER
                           WITH HIS COMPANIONS.

          A
                  LTHOUGH Dominic, as  we have seen, was  imbued with
                  the desire to do good to souls, it did not, as some mistaken
                  people  might  imagine,  tend  to  make  him  melancholy  or
          mournful.  On  the  contrary,  he  was  the  life  of  the  recreation time,
          though  he  very  wisely  knew  how  to  turn  every  opportunity  to
          account.  When  others  had  something  to  say  or  a  story  to  tell,  he
          never interrupted or criticised; but when conversation flagged, he had
          an  inexhaustible  fund  of  entertaining  information  and  anecdotes
          which were highly interesting to his companies. He knew just when
          to seize the opportunity of speaking, if it were necessary to deal with
          grumbling or murmuring, or something not approved of.
             His manner was so cheerful and attractive that he counted among
          his companions even those who were least disposed to piety, or were
          of an opposite nature to his own, and they always took in good part
          whatever insinuation or hint he might give them.
             Once when the boys were at play in an open space, a man came
          up and joined in the conversation. He was amusing at first, and had a
          story or two that suited the curiosity of young people. But when he
          had made himself at home a little; he went on to speak of religious
          subjects and priests and the like, and treated them with ridicule and
          disrespect. Many of the boys noticed the change in his conversation
          and went off to play; others stayed on. But then Dominic arrived. He
          stopped for a moment to listen, but immediately saw what the man
                                         26]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO

              was about, and without any hesitation said to the boys round him:
              "Don't stay here listening to such a degraded man; he is only trying to
              corrupt souls." The boys were accustomed to Dominic's influence in
              regard to such things, and all moved away, leaving  the man alone.
              The latter retired discomfited, and never tried his persuasive arts in
              that neighbourhood again.
                 This influence of Dominic's gradually increased, so that he could
              usually persuade the boys against any course in which he saw that evil
              might  lurk.  There  was  at  the  Oratory,  at  the  time,  a  little  society
              composed  of  the  better  and  more  able  boys,  who  endeavoured  to
              check any wrongdoing amongst the rest, and to deal with any unruly
              ones amongst them. Savio belonged to it and played a foremost part
              in it. Whatever little presents came to him he reserved them to add
              weight to his persuasion. Sometimes he would seize an opportunity
              in the games, when a boy on whom he had designs was a partner of
              his,  to  ask  him  to  promise  to  go  to  Confession  with  him  on  the
              following Saturday. As Saturday usually seemed a long way off, the
              boy generally consented; but Dominic did not let him forget it, and
              when Saturday came he would take the boy off to church, as pleased
              with the success  of his little ruse  as  a sportsman is in securing his
              prize. In this way it often happened that a boy, on whom a hundred
              sermons  would  be  lost,  would  at  once  succumb  to  some  novel
              method invented by Dominic's zeal for souls.
                 However, it occasionally happened, that on the appointed day, the
              boy who had promised to accompany him to Confession, would be
              missing. As soon as Dominic saw him again he would say: "Ah, you
              disappointed  me;  you  didn't  keep  your  promise."  The  boy  would
              bring  forward  some  excuse,  but  he  was  never  able  to  convince
              Dominic, who easily explained to the boy that he had been caught in
              one of the devil's tricks for putting off Confession. He would then go
              on to show him how happy he would be afterwards  if he made  a
              good Confession, and get him to make another promise. It always
              happened that these boys would go to Dominic afterwards and tell
              him how glad they were for having followed his advice, and that they
              would go frequently to the Sacraments in future.
                 It is a common thing, that among a great number of boys, a few
              are  left  more  or  less  severely  alone,  whether  on  account  of  their
              peculiar character, or of some defect, or something uninviting about

                                             27]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

          them;  sometimes,  too,  these  are  the  object  of  the  ridicule  and
          torment  of  their  companions,  and  are  sorely  in  need  of  a  friend.
          Dominic was always on the look out for these. He was frequently in
          their company, entertaining them in one way or another. Others, who
          through ignorance or  neglect,  were  disposed  to  be  mischievous  or
          bad,  Dominic  took  in  hand,  and  always  brought  them  to  a  better
          frame of mind. With the sick again he was in great demand; so that in
          one way or another Savio was a real apostle and put into practice his
          great ideal of drawing souls to God.


















































                                         28]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[CHAPTER XII
              HIS SPIRIT OF PRAYER. HIS DEVOTION TO THE HOLY
                      MOTHER OF GOD. THE MONTH OF MAY.

              D
                        OMINIC  was  evidently  endowed  with  special  gifts  from
                        God,  and  among  them  was  his  assiduity  and  fervour  in
                        prayer. It seemed to be part of his very nature to converse
              with  God,  and  no  matter  where  he  was,  or  what  noises  or  games
              might be going on around him, his recollection was never disturbed,
              and  his  ejaculations  were  none  the  less  frequent.  At  the  general
              prayers of the boys, his manner can only be described as that of an
              angel; his  attitude was  devotion itself; he never seemed to want to
              rest even his elbows, but, kneeling, and with hands joined, his eyes
              cast down, he gave himself up to communing with God. To look at
              him thus was to be edified.
                 In 1854 the Count Cays was elected President of the Sodality of
              St. Aloysius, that was  established at the Oratory. The first time he
              was present at the functions of the Sodality, he saw a boy at prayer
              with such an air of rapt devotion, that he was immediately struck by
              him.  He  inquired  about  him  afterwards,  and  of  course,  it  was  our
              young  friend. Dominic always  managed  to spend some part of his
              recreation in the chapel, generally getting a companion to go in with
              him, though he need not stay as long as Dominic did.
                 His devotion to Our Blessed Lady was like a burning fire within
              him. Every day he practised some act of mortification in her honour.
              Attracted  by  her  heavenly  beauty  he  had  no  desire  of  gazing  on
              things of earthly mould, and the thought of her purity and modesty
                                             29]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

          prevented him from taking interest in the ordinary entertaining sights
          of the town which so much attract the average boy. This abstraction
          or deep recollection, when out in the streets, was frequently remarked
          upon by his companions, and he generally explained it by saying that
          he was thinking of something far more interesting in connection with
          Our Lady  and Heaven. To her he offered special devotions in the
          course  of  the  day,  particularly  on  Friday,  in  honour  of  the  seven
          dolours, and he placed his own purity of soul in the keeping of that
          immaculate Virgin.
             It was therefore a natural development that he should be carried
          away  with  special  fervour  during  the  month  of  May.  There  were
          always extra services in the church for the benefit of the public, and
          the boys took part in them. But Dominic was not satisfied with that.
          He  arranged  with  certain  companions  to  perform  extra  devotions
          every  day,  and  he  prepared  a  stock  of  examples  and  anecdotes
          concerning the devotion to Our Lady; with the aid of these he urged
          not a few boys to make an effort to celebrate the month with fervour.
          Needless to say, he received Holy Communion every day during that
          period and was a shining example to all those that came in contact
          with him.
             A  little  incident  is  told  in  connection  with  this  month.  It  was
          proposed  by  someone  that  a  little  altar  should  be  erected  in  the
          dormitory to which Dominic belonged, and a collection was made all
          round  for  contributions  towards  its  expense.  Savio  found  himself
          among the number of boys who had no pocket money at the time;
          yet  it  was  not  to  be  thought  of  that  he  should  be  out  of  the
          contribution to so good a cause. He soon conceived a plan. He had
          among his books one that was of some value, which he had received
          as  a prize. He proposed that this  should be sold and the proceeds
          given to the altar. Others thought they would adopt the same plan;
          they  accordingly  got  together  a  few  of  their  things  that  might  be
          desirable in the eyes of companions, and arranged to have a sort of
          lottery. Purchasers were soon found, and the result was ample for the
          decoration  of the  altar.  Its  adornment  was  to  be  done  after  night-
          prayers, by special permission, but Dominic was expressly advised to
          go to bed, as he had not been well of late; he obeyed, but it was quite
          a sacrifice for him to be deprived of doing something that he thought
          tended directly to the honour of her, of whom he was  one of the

                                         30]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO

              most devout clients.































































                                             31]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[CHAPTER XIII
          HIS FREQUENTATION AND DEVOUT RECEPTION OF
                              THE SACRAMENTS.

          T
                 HE confirmed experience of those who have assisted in the
                 spiritual  training  or  the  general  education  of  the  young  is,
                 that  the  Sacraments  of  Confession  and  Holy  Communion
          are  the  best  safeguards  and  the  strongest  supports  for  that  critical
          period of their life. If you can show me a boy who frequently receives
          the Holy Sacraments, it will be enough to convince me that he will
          pass  through  the  years  of  youth,  reach  the  age  of  manhood  and
          maturity, and, if God so disposes, arrive at a venerable old age, and
          all during that time will be an example to those who know him. This
          should  be  impressed  upon  the  young  so  that  they  may  form  this
          excellent habit: it should be seriously considered and grasped by all
          who share in the education of the young, so that they may assist them
          to put it into practice.
             Apart from certain establishments, few in number, it was not usual
          in the time we are treating of, for children or adults to go frequently
          to the Sacraments, and so Dominic Savio had only been accustomed
          to go once a month to Confession and Communion before he came
          to the Oratory. But from that time he began to go more often. In fact
          it had been stated in the pulpit of the Oratory Chapel, that if the boys
          were really desirous of walking in the path of virtue, and persevering
          in  it,  they  should  practise  three  things:  to  go  regularly  to  the
          Sacrament of Penance; to approach the Holy Table very frequently;
          to  open  their  heart  freely  to  their  confessor.  Dominic  had  noted
                                         32]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO

              down these counsels, for in such things he had a special knowledge
              of what was important.
                 He chose his confessor, and only had the one during his stay at
              the Oratory. In order to make quite sure that everything was correct,
              and to form a right estimation of his conscience, he made a general
              confession. Then he began to go every fortnight, and then weekly.
              His habit of monthly Communion was soon altered to a weekly one,
              and then to several times a week, and then to a daily one. At one time
              he seemed to become scrupulous and wished to confess oftener, but
              his  confessor  forbade  him  to  go  more  than  once  a  week,  and  he
              adhered to this direction.
                 But in this confessor he had the utmost confidence, and opened
              his  whole soul to him. Even out of confession he often consulted
              him  about  the  affairs  of  his  soul,  and  in  regard  to  a  change  of
              confessor he very acutely said: "The confessor is the soul's physician.
              You do not change your doctor unless he proves unworthy of your
              confidence, or unable to deal with your complaint. Neither of these
              cases applies to me. I have entire confidence in my confessor, and I
              do  not  know  of  any  diseases  of  the  soul  that  he  cannot  cure."
              However, this confessor directed him to go to another priest from
              time to time, especially at the monthly exercises for a good death; and
              the boy did so.
                 In these matters, indeed, he had special gifts. He used to say that
              he could not possibly be in need of spiritual comfort or strength; for
              he got all the guidance he required from his confessor, and all the
              desires of his soul were satisfied in the delights of Holy Communion;
              nothing could be added to his happiness, until it was time for him to
              be admitted to the unveiled presence of Our Lord, whom he now
              beheld on the Altar with the eyes of Faith.
                 It was this frame of mind that conduced to Dominic's perpetual
              calm and cheerfulness, and the special joy that seemed to accompany
              his daily life. However, it must not be imagined for a moment that he
              was not observant in the extreme, lest anything should prevent his
              being prepared to go daily to the Holy Sacrament; on the contrary,
              his conduct was on all occasions singularly without blemish. I have
              questioned those who were with him during his three years amongst
              us, and who lived the same student's life with him, and not one of
              them  could,  after  due  reflection,  bring  forward  any  defect  or

                                             33]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

          negligence,  or  suggest  any  virtue  in  which  he  was  lacking;  and  yet
          boys  have  a  high  standard  when  judging  of  such  things  in  their
          companions.
             In regard to his actual reception of Holy Communion, he used to
          say a special prayer of preparation the night before. In the morning
          he  prepared  with  the  other  boys  during  Mass,  and  with  his  own
          particular devotion; but his thanksgiving cannot be said to have ever
          terminated. It was quite an ordinary occurrence, that, if not specially
          called  or  aroused,  he  would  not  remember  breakfast  time  or  even
          school time, remaining in prayer, or rather in a sort of contemplation
          and  adoration  of  the  goodness  of  Our  Divine  Lord,  who
          communicates with souls in His own ineffable manner.
             If he could spend an hour during the day in the presence of the
          Blessed  Sacrament,  it  was  his  utmost  delight;  but he  always  found
          time for a visit every day, and got someone to go with him if possible.
          His favourite prayers were a series of acts in reparation to the Sacred
          Heart of Jesus; they were a well known devotional practice, and to be
          found in most prayerbooks; in order that his communions might be
          more fruitful and meritorious, and that there might be a motive of
          renewed fervour every day, he always had a definite intention in view.
          His intentions were thus distributed over the week:

             SUNDAY. - In honour of the Blessed Trinity.
             MONDAY.  -  For  the  welfare  of  spiritual  and  temporal
          benefactors.
             TUESDAY. - In honour of my Patron Saint, Saint Dominic, and
          of my Guardian Angel.
             WEDNESDAY. - In honour of Our Lady's Seven Dolours, for
          the conversion of sinners.
             THURSDAY. - For the Souls in Purgatory.
             FRIDAY. - In honour of the Sacred Passion of Christ.
             SATURDAY. - In honour of Our Lady, to obtain her protection
          in life and death.

             Whatever  devotions  were  practised  in  honour  of  the  Blessed
          Sacrament,  he  took  part  in  them  with  eager  joy  and  delight;  and
          would accompany the priest when taking Holy Viaticum, if he were
          allowed. One day a priest was passing across a muddy street with the

                                         34]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO

              Blessed Sacrament, when Dominic was near. There had been a great
              deal of rain and it was muddy all round. But the boy took no head of
              that.  He  knelt  in  the  mud  and  made  his  act  of  adoration.  A
              companion  remonstrated  that  he  need  not  have  knelt  in  the  mud:
              that  God  did  not  command  it,  and  did  not  wish  him  to  dirty  his
              clothes in that way. But that was not at all Dominic's view of such
              things; he replied that trousers as well as knees belonged to God; and
              should therefore be employed in His honour. "Whenever I approach
              the Sacramental Presence," he said, "I would not only throw myself
              in  the  mud,  but  even  into  a  fiery  furnace,  for  thus  I  should  be
              consumed with that fire of infinite charity, which moved Our Lord to
              institute the Most Holy Sacrament.
                 On another occasion he noticed that a soldier was standing while
              the Blessed Sacrament was being carried by; Dominic did not like to
              invite the  soldier to  kneel  down,  so he  took  out his  handkerchief,
              spread it on the ground, and made a sign that he might kneel on it.
              The soldier was a little confused at this hidden rebuke, but he left the
              handkerchief alone and knelt down where he was, in the middle of
              the street.
                 One of Dominic's delights was to be dressed as a cleric for the
              great Procession of the Blessed Sacrament on the Feast of Corpus
              Christi. His  whole bearing  revealed the depth of his  Faith and the
              excess of his love.


























                                             35]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[CHAPTER XIV
                            HIS MORTIFICATIONS.

          I
               T  will  be  rightly  conjectured  that  many  reasons  forbade  that
               Dominic  should  undertake  any  extraordinary  penance:  there
               was  his  age  (he  was  only  fourteen  or  fifteen);  there  was  his
          delicate health; there was the innocence of his life. But he knew that
          it  is  difficult  to  maintain  fervour  and  purity  of  soul  without  some
          austerity,  and this  consideration  made  him  ready  for  penances  and
          mortification; and by mortifications I do not here allude to the insults
          and unpleasantness that he had to bear, or to his continual restraint
          over his senses, whether in class, study or recreation. This form of
          penance was a habit with him.
             I refer now to actual penances, painful to the body. In his fervour,
          and his devotion to the Mother of God, he had resolved to fast on
          bread  and  water  every  Saturday;  but  his  confessor  forbade  it;  he
          wished to fast during Lent; but after a week it came to the knowledge
          of the Director of the House, and that too was forbidden. He wished
          at least to do without breakfast, but consideration for his health made
          it prudent to forbid that also. What then was he to do to satisfy his
          desire  for  some  bodily  mortifications.  As  he  was  forbidden  to  do
          anything that affected his food, he began to afflict his body in other
          ways. He put some some sharp things into his bed, so that he might
          not be able to repose in comfort: he wanted a kind of hair shirt; but
          all these things were soon prohibited. He thought of something else.
          During  the autumn and winter he managed  to escape having  extra
          blankets for his bed, so that during the cold of January he had only
                                         36]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO

              the summer coverings on his bed. This was discovered, because, one
              morning  he  was  unwell,  and  had  to  remain  in  bed;  and  when  the
              Director came to see  him, he saw at once that he had insufficient
              covering for that severe weather. "Why did you do this?" the Director
              asked, "did you want to die of cold?"
                 "Oh, I shall not die of cold," he answered. "When in the stable at
              Bethlehem, or hanging on the Cross, Our Lord had less to cover Him
              than I have now." He was then forbidden to undertake any penance
              at  all  without  express  permission;  and  this  command,  though
              difficult, was obeyed.
                 Later on I saw that he was in some difficulty. He said he could not
              reconcile  the  command  of  the  Gospel  to  do  penance,  with  the
              prohibition he had received. "The penance God wishes from you," I
              said,  "is  simply  obedience.  If  you  obey,  that  will  suffice  for
              everything."
                 "Can you not allow me to do some other penance?"
                 "The only penance you are to do, is to bear patiently all that God
              sends you in this life."
                 "But those things must be put up with by necessity."
                 "Very well," I replied, "whatever you have to suffer by necessity,
              offer it to God, and it will become a virtue, and meritorious in the
              sight of God."
                 This counsel comforted his misgivings and he was never disturbed
              in that way again.
























                                             37]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[CHAPTER XV
            THE MORTIFICATION OF HIS EXTERNAL SENSES.

          A
                  NY casual observer of Dominic's outward behaviour would
                  have thought his  composure so natural, that it must have
                  been part of his character from birth; but those who were
          intimately  associated  with  him,  and  had  the  care  of  his  education,
          know very well that it was  only gained by long  and serious  effort,
          assisted by the grace of God.
             To obtain the guard he had over his eyes, he had to make so great
          and constant an effort, that he once told a friend that his head often
          ached in consequence of it; but the restraint he had acquired was so
          complete  that  no  one  ever  saw  him  give  an  unguarded  glance,  or
          indulge his sight to the least degree. The eyes are like two windows,
          he would say, and it depends  upon yourself whether you admit an
          angel or a devil by them.
             One  day  a  boy had  brought  in,  doubtless  unthinkingly,  a  paper
          with  some  unbecoming  pictures  in  it.  A  group  of  boys  gathered
          round to see them, and Dominic thought some sacred pictures were
          being shown. So he came up to look also; but as soon as he perceived
          of what nature the pictures were, he was surprised, and taking hold of
          the paper he tore it into pieces. The boys stood around in silence;
          then he quietly said: "Our eyes were given to see the beautiful things
          God  has  created,  and  you  use  them  to  gaze  on  such  unseemly
          pictures,  provided  by  the  malice  of  satan  for  the  ruin  of  souls.
          Perhaps you have forgotten what you have so often heard, that one
          evil glance may stain the soul with sin; and yet you indulge your eyes
                                         38]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO

              with such objects as that."
                 Some began to make excuses, but he easily showed them that they
              were but the snares of the devil, who could draw them on to sin by
              these means; and in the end no reply could be made to his arguments
              and recommendations.
                 To  this  care  of  the  eyes  he  joined  particular  reserve  in
              conversation. He never interrupted anyone who might be speaking,
              and he often broke off his own sentences in the middle, if another
              showed that he had something to say. His masters and associates all
              agree  that  he  was  never  observed  to  have  said  a  single  idle  word,
              whether in  class  or in  study,  or  during  the  fulfilment  of  any  duty.
              Even  when  he  was  the  object  of  unkindness  or  insults,  he  had  a
              careful reserve over his words.
                 One day he had spoken to a companion about a bad habit he had
              contracted. The latter forgot that this was a kindness, and answered
              with insults, and even struck and kicked him. Dominic was older and
              bigger  than  the  other  boy,  and  might  easily  have  returned  this
              treatment; but he sought no revenge but that of Christian charity: at
              first he became red in the face, but stifling all feeling of resentment
              he said: "I forgive you; you have done wrong; but do not try that sort
              of behaviour on others."
                 In  regard  to  the  mortification  of  all  his  senses,  I  shall  restrict
              myself  to  a  few  incidents.  In  winter-time  he  had  a  novel  way  of
              treating  his  hands,  for  he  was  subject  to  chilblains,  and  these  he
              exposed to the cold and wet as much as he could, so as to increase
              their size and painfulness; he even pricked them to make them smart
              the more. He thought that he was thus imitating, in a small degree,
              the  wounds  inflicted  on  the  person  of  our  Divine  Lord.  His
              companions assert that in the very cold weather he went along slowly
              to school, so as to be exposed to the weather as much as possible.
                 Wherever  there  are  a  number  of  young  people  living  together,
              there  are  sure  to  be  some  who  are  ready  with  complaints.  The
              arrangements  of  the  house,  the  discipline,  the  bed  time,  and  such
              things, all form the subject of complaint from different persons, and
              occasionally  great  disturbances  are  caused.  Savio  was  quite  the
              opposite of this. He rejoiced if there were something that might be
              taken  exception  to,  and,  particularly  in  his  diet,  he  was  always
              satisfied and equally pleased.

                                             39]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO


             He was  economical to a degree, regarding the food as  a gift of
          God, and therefore not to be despised, even in the smallest way. He
          was always ready to do a service to others, particularly to the sick, and
          he eagerly seized occasions for doing this, since his health made him
          unable to undertake anything of a tiring nature.
             Little  examples  of  his  mortification,  charity,  self-forgetfulness,
          humility,  and  the  like,  might  easily  be  multiplied,  but  these  things
          were part of Dominic's very life, and went to make up that perfect
          whole which constitutes a pleasing offering in God's sight.
















































                                         40]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[CHAPTER XVI
                   THE CONFRATERNITY OF THE IMMACULATE
                                      CONCEPTION.

              S
                    OMETHING has been said above about Dominic's devotion
                    to  Our  Blessed  Lady,  and  it  may  be  well  imagined  that  the
                    circumstances  of  December,  1854,  provided  occasions  for
              extra fervour that were not lost upon him.
                 On the eighth of that month the Sovereign Pontiff defined the
              Dogma  of  Our  Lady's  Immaculate  Conception,  and  the  Catholic
              world was filled as with a wave of devotion. Young Savio was always
              practical  in  his  manifestation  of  fervour.  His  idea  was  not only to
              celebrate  the  event,  but  to  set  on  foot  something  that  might  be  a
              permanent remembrance, and might be productive in years to come
              of a continual stream of devout clients of Our Lady.
                 He  therefore  set  to  work  amongst  his  closest  friends,  and
              proposed to them the formation of a sodality or association, to be
              called the Sodality of the Immaculate Conception. Its object was to
              obtain the special protection of Our Lady during life and particularly
              at  the  hour  of  death.  The  means  proposed  were  to  practice  and
              promote acts of devotion in honour of the Mother of God, and the
              adoption of the practice of frequent Communion by all members. It
              was  to  have  a  special  rule  and  these  were  the  subject  of  long
              consideration, so that they were only in their final shape by June 8th,
              1856, about nine months before his death. These were read out by
              him before the Altar of Our Lady on that day. The articles were of an
              exhaustive character, twenty-one in number, providing for the regular
                                             41]]></page><page Index="54"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

          meeting  of  the  members,  the  spiritual  duties  undertaken,  and  the
          means for gaining the chief ends mentioned above. These rules were
          all submitted to the judgment of the Director, and concluded with an
          appeal to Our Blessed  Lady to assist the associates  and bless their
          efforts.  Several  of  those  who  took  part  in  the  formation  of  this
          society were distinguished, like Dominic, for their piety and talents.
          One  in  particular  was  gifted  with  exceptional  brilliance,  and  being
          afterwards  ordained  as  a  secular  priest,  he  had  a  most  fruitful
          apostolate,  and  took  a  large  share  in  the  arrangements  for  the
          opening of the Sanctuary of Our Lady, Help of Christians, at Turin,
          during the octave of which celebrations he was called to his reward.
          While still a cleric he founded the Sodality of the Blessed Sacrament,
          which has since been a traditional sodality in our schools, and by its
          means effected great good among the boys of the Oratory.









































                                         42]]></page><page Index="55"><![CDATA[CHAPTER XVII
                         DOMINIC'S INTIMATE ASSOCIATES.

              F
                     ROM  much  of  the  foregoing  it  will  be  concluded  that
                     Dominic  was  a  friend  to  all,  and  was  regarded  by  all  as  a
                     friend. If  anyone did not feel drawn to him in a particular
              manner, it was impossible not to treat him with respectful regard. He
              was of such excellent dispositions, partly from his natural gifts, partly
              from his training and efforts, that he was often given charge of boys
              who needed some special care and skillful handling, so that he might
              gradually  bring  them  up  to  the  standard  that  flourished  at  the
              Oratory.  In  carrying  out  these  charges  he  was  particularly  apt  at
              profiting  of  every  occasion  that  presented  itself,  whether  in
              recreation, or walks, or church.
                 But if he was regarded as a friend by the boys in general, he was
              something  more  to  those  who  were  associated  with  him  in  the
              Sodality of the Immaculate Conception. These were his co-workers,
              counsellors,  and  intimate  friends.  They  were  brought  together  for
              their extra devotions, their talks and arrangements, their discussions
              concerning  the  boys  who  were  entrusted  to  their  care  for  special
              guidance, and all other items concerning the apostolate of those who
              belonged  to  the Sodality,  and  which  was  far  reaching  in  its  scope.
              These conferences and propositions were made with the approval of
              the Director, but were held by the boys themselves.
                 Savio was  the prime mover in these  meetings, and, in fact, was
              looked up to as the teacher and guiding spirit. There were, however,
              several prominent members, who were very like him in their zeal and
                                             43]]></page><page Index="56"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

          piety, and in their skill and capabilities in assisting in the training of
          their younger companions. Many of these are still living, and engaged
          in  the  priesthood,  or  in  prominent  positions;  it  would  therefore,
          perhaps, not be tactful to speak of them directly. But I have thought
          it useful to call attention to two of them who have already been called
          away  to  their  eternal  reward.  They  are  Camillus  Gavio,  and  John
          Massaglia. The former only remained at the Oratory two months, but
          it was long enough to leave a lasting remembrance.
             His piety had always been conspicuous, and with this he possessed
          remarkable talents, particularly for painting  and sculpture; so much
          so, that the municipality of Tortona, his native city, had awarded him
          a  scholarship,  so  that  he  might  come  to  the  Schools  of  Turin,  to
          continue his studies and artistic training.
             Shortly before his arrival at the Oratory he had recovered from a
          serious  illness.  This  doubtless  accounted  for  much  of  his  quiet,
          retiring life, for he was practically only then convalescent, and at a
          distance from his home and friends. Moreover, he knew none of the
          boys at the Oratory, and all these circumstances combined to make
          him rather a spectator of, than a partner in the games, and he was
          often noticed with a far away, abstracted look. Savio soon made his
          acquaintance and got into conversation. He had quickly elicited the
          main facts of the boy's life, including his late illness. But this last item
          should be described in the words of the actual speakers. The new-
          comer had described briefly his illness, which was concerned with a
          weakness of the heart, and had brought him to death's door.
             "You  desired  very  much  to  be  cured,  I  suppose?"  enquired
          Dominic.
             "No, not a great deal; I only desired that the Will of God might be
          done."
             No more than this was required to convince Savio that his new
          acquaintance  was  gifted  with  extraordinary  piety,  and  he  secretly
          rejoiced at this acquisition to the Oratory; he therefore followed up
          the boy's response by remarking: " Whoever desires to do the Will of
          God,  is  anxious  for  his  own  sanctification;  do  you  ever  feel  this
          desire?"
             "Oh yes, it has long been my chief ambition."
             "Very good; the number of our friends  increases  daily; you will
          join  our  inner  circle  of those  who have  the  same  ambition  as  you

                                         44]]></page><page Index="57"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO

              have."
                 The new boy agreed, and a discussion was held as to his future
              conduct.  Savio  pointed  out  to  him,  that  at  the  Oratory  sanctity
              consisted principally in being happy; that the boys took every care to
              avoid sin, as the great enemy, to do all duties as well as possible, and
              to  perform  the  practices  of  piety  with  exactitude.  Servite  Domine  in
              latitia is to be our motto.
                 This advice of Dominic's seemed to fall like a healing balm on the
              soul of Camillus. He became a close companion of Dominic's, and
              from  him  learnt  the  secrets  of  great  holiness  that  he  had  himself
              acquired. With such a guide, and with his own excellent good will and
              dispositions, it was no wonder he made rapid progress in virtue, so as
              to become prominent even among those who were themselves all of
              a very high standard of exactitude and piety.
                 However,  his  rapid  progress  in  piety  was  like  his  swift  course
              towards  heaven.  The  illness  he  had  described  to  Dominic had  left
              effects that could not be removed by medical aid, and it was soon
              evident that he was in a very dangerous condition. Every care from
              physicians and friends was his, but in vain. It was time for him to go
              to that Divine Lord whose Will he had so faithfully sought to do, and
              after  receiving  the  Sacraments  with  great  edification,  he  died  on
              December 30th, 1856.
                 Dominic was his constant attendant during his illness, and would
              readily have watched by him all night, but he was not allowed. When
              he was told that his companion had died, he asked to go and see the
              body,  and  looking  at  the  face  of  his  friend  he  said  with  emotion:
              "Farewell, Gavio; I am quite sure that you have gone to Heaven; so
              prepare a place for me. However, I shall always be a friend to you,
              and shall pray for the repose of your soul as long as I am left here on
              earth."
                 The Sodality of the Immaculate Conception had special rules for
              the  prayers  and  Communions  to  be  offered  for  the  deceased
              members, and Dominic immediately arranged for them to be carried
              out.  His  words  and  recommendations  to  his  companions  on  this
              occasion  were typical of  that  gravity,  which  he  always  displayed  in
              regard to things of the spiritual life, of the importance of which he
              always had an intimate conviction.


                                             45]]></page><page Index="58"><![CDATA[CHAPTER XVIII
                  DOMINIC SAVIO AND JOHN MASSIGLIA.

          T
                 HERE was a boy at the Oratory whose character and career
                 bore  a  striking  similarity  to  Dominic's.  He  had  come  to
                 Turin at the same time; he had come from a little place quite
          close  to  Mondonio,  so  that  they  were  practically  from  the  one
          district.  He  had  the  same  intentions  as  Dominic,  to  embrace  the
          ecclesiastical  state,  and  he  was  inspired  with  a  like  eagerness  to
          advance in the science of the saints. This was John Massiglia.
             He  had  been  talking  one  day  to  his  friend  about  their  future
          hopes, and after their exchange of ideas Dominic said: "It will not be
          sufficient for us merely to desire to become priests; there are means
          to be adopted to acquire the virtues that are suitable to that state."
          John replied that he was fully aware of it, but that he had confidence
          that they would have the grace to acquire them, if they were chosen
          to be among the ministers of Jesus Christ.
             There had been some special sermons and exercises in preparation
          for the Easter Communions, and these two had taken part in them
          with singular devotion. After their Communion Dominic said to his
          companion:  "I  very  much  desire  that  we  should  be  true  friends;
          friends,  that  is,  in  regard  to the  affairs  of  the  soul.  I propose  that
          from now we each admonish the other in regard to anything that may
          be thought useful for our spiritual advancement. If you see anything
          wrong in my conduct tell me immediately, that I may correct it; or if
          you think of any good I ought to perform, point it out to me."

                                         46]]></page><page Index="59"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO

                 His friend promised to do so, "though," he said, "there will be no
              opportunity, and on the condition that you do the same for me, who
              am in much greater need of such an arrangement." Dominic replied
              that that was not the time for compliments, but that henceforth they
              would help each other in the progress of their soul.
                 From that time, Dominic Savio and John Massiglia were intimate
              friends, and it was a true and perfect friendship, since it was founded
              upon real charity, and nourished by the frequent intercommunion of
              those pious suggestions and experiences which are prompted only by
              solid virtue.
                 At the end of the scholastic year, after the examinations, all the
              boys were allowed to go to their homes for the vacation, but some
              always preferred to remain at the Oratory, both for the advantages of
              extra  study  and  to  continue  their  exercises  of  piety,  which  could
              scarcely be carried on at home. Savio and Massiglia were among the
              number. But I knew that both were eagerly expected by their parents
              to  spend  the  holidays  at  home,  and  that  a  change  and  rest  were
              necessary after their year's work at their books. I therefore met them
              both together and said:
                 "Why do you not prefer to go home for a time?" No answer was
              at first forthcoming; both began to smile. "What is the meaning of
              that smile?" I enquired. Then Dominic replied, "We know that our
              parents would like us to go home, and in one way we are anxious to
              go; but as long as birds are in their cage, they are safe from the hawk;
              once out of it, there is risk of falling into the toils of the enemy of
              souls."
                 But in spite of their good intentions and their desires to stay, I
              insisted on their going home for a time. They obeyed, but only stayed
              away the minimum time that I had appointed.
                 If a detailed description were to be given of this friend, it would
              be very similar to the one being given of Dominic himself, for they
              had  the  same  ideals,  and  were  led  in  the  same  paths  of  virtue.
              Massiglia was of far more robust build than Dominic, and his health
              never  gave  anxiety;  in  fact  he  was  most  promising  in  every  way;
              particularly in regard to his progress in his studies. He had finished
              his course of rhetoric and had received the clerical habit, for which
              he had so ardently longed. But he was destined to enjoy his happiness
              only for a few months. Some indisposition, slight though it appeared

                                             47]]></page><page Index="60"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

          to be, caused us to insist on his studies being laid aside for a time,
          and as he did not appear to recover he was sent to his native place, by
          the  advice  of  the  doctors.  While  there  he  wrote  to  his  friend  the
          following letter:
             "My dear Friend,
             "When I left the Oratory, I thought I should be away only for a
          short time, so that I did not think it necessary to bring any books or
          school things with me. But now it appears that my recovery will take
          time, and in fact the issue of my illness is quite uncertain. The doctor
          says I am improving, but I think I am gradually getting  worse: we
          shall see which of us is right. My chief regret is that I must be away
          from the Oratory and from you, and have had to give up most of the
          exercises of piety which we used to practise. My only consolation is
          in  the  recollection  of  the  days  when  we  went  together  to  Holy
          Communion, and the preparation we used to make for them.
             "However,  although  we  are  separated  in  body,  we  shall  remain
          united  in  heart  and  spirit.  I  want to  ask you  to  get  from  my  desk
          some  manuscripts  and  the  Latin  copy  of  the  Imitation  of  Christ,
          which is  beside  them,  and  send  both  on to  me.  You  may imagine
          how tired I am of doing  nothing. The doctor will not hear of my
          studying  at  all.  I  have  plenty  of  time  for  consideration,  and  often
          wonder whether I am to be cured, or to go back again to the Oratory,
          or whether this is  destined to be my last illness. In any case  I feel
          ready to submit with joy to the Holy Will of God.
             "If you have any suggestion to make tell me of it. Do not forget to
          pray for me, and if we may not have the opportunity of enjoying our
          former  friendship  I  trust  we  shall  enjoy together one  day  a  happy
          eternity.
             "Remember me to all my friends, particularly to the Sodality of
          Our Lady Immaculate.
             "Believe me,
                                "Your affectionate friend,
                                                     "JOHN MASSIGLIA."

             Dominic at once carried out his friend's request, and enclosed the
          following letter:



                                         48]]></page><page Index="61"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO

                 "My dear Massiglia,
                 "Your letter was a source of consolation to me, and to all your
              friends, for it at least showed that you were alive, a fact which we
              were  beginning  to  doubt,  and  did  not  know  whether  to  sing  the
              Gloria  Patri  or  the  De  Profundis.  The  things  you  have  asked  for  are
              being  sent.  I  will  only  remark  that  though  Thomas  à  Kempis  is  a
              good  friend,  he  is  dead  and  gone;  you  must  search  for him in his
              writings, and make his counsel living again by putting it into practice.
                 "I see that you are desirous for the opportunities we have here for
              the performance of the spiritual exercises. You are right. When I am
              away from the Oratory I feel the same need. I used to try to make up
              for it by visiting the Blessed Sacrament every day, and getting some
              companions to go with me if they would. Besides the Imitation I used
              to  read  the  Hidden  Treasure,  by  St.  Leonard  of  Port  Maurice.  You
              could do the same perhaps, if you feel disposed.
                 "You say that you do not know whether you will return to the
              Oratory or not. Truth to tell, I also feel that my health is showing
              alarming symptoms, and I have a presentiment that I am advancing
              with rapid strides towards the end of my studies and of my life. We
              can  at  least  pray  for  each  other,  that  we  may  have  the  grace  of  a
              happy death. Whichever one of us goes to Heaven first must prepare
              a place for the other, and will be able to stretch out a helping hand to
              lead him to his heavenly home.
                 "May God keep us in His Grace, and help us to become saints, for
              we may not have long to live. All your friends are longing for your
              return to the Oratory and send their kind remembrances to you. For
              myself
                                           "I remain,
                                 "Your most affectionate friend,
                                                          "DOMINIC SAVIO."

                 This illness of young Massiglia, as we have said, appeared slight at
              first; more than once he seemed quite recovered; but again relapsed,
              until he was quite suddenly brought to the point of death.
                 Fr. Vafrè, who was his Director while at Mondonio, writes: "He
              had time to receive the last comforts  of Religion, and did so with
              greatest edification; he died the death of the just man who leaves this
              world to go straight to his reward."

                                             49]]></page><page Index="62"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

             Savio was profoundly grieved at the death of his close friend, and
          although resigned to the Will of God, he mourned his loss for some
          time. It was almost the only occasion that I had seen his gentle face
          covered with the tears of sorrow. His one consolation was to pray for
          his friend's soul, and to get others to pray for him. More than once
          he said: "Massiglia has gone to join Gavio in heaven, when shall I go
          to join them in the bliss of Paradise?"
             As  long  as  Dominic  lived,  he  had  his  friend  often  in  mind,
          particularly at Mass and at the spiritual exercises; he never ceased to
          recommend to God the soul of that friend, who, he felt, had been of
          such assistance to him. In fact this loss had more serious results than
          one would think, for it seriously affected the already weakened frame
          of the friend and his health, which had never been robust.











































                                         50]]></page><page Index="63"><![CDATA[CHAPTER XIX
                     SPECIAL GRACES GRANTED TO DOMINIC.
                           SOME PARTICULAR INCIDENTS.

              A
                      S  far  as  the  generality  of  boys  is  concerned,  it  would  be
                      considered  quite  extraordinary  for  them  to  maintain  the
                      high standard of conduct, and the continual endeavour after
              virtue  that  has  been  described  above;  that  innocence  of  life  and
              performance of good works, penances, and acts of special fervour.
              But these things made up the ordinary rule of Savio's life. Nothing
              short of extraordinary, again, were his wonderful faith, his constant
              hope, his ardent charity, and his perseverance till his last breath.
                 I  now  wish  to  describe  certain  facts  that  are  really  out  of  the
              common,  and  which  may  perhaps  some  day  be  the  subject  of
              criticism. It may be well to point out to the reader, that the facts to be
              related are very like others related in the Bible or in the Lives of the
              Saints; moreover I am relating what occurred under my own notice,
              and the incidents are given with scrupulous care; the conclusions to
              be drawn must be left for the discreet reader.
                 Very often when Dominic went into the church, principally on his
              Communion days, or when the Blessed Sacrament was exposed, he
              fell into what was  clearly a sort of rapture or ecstasy; and thus  he
              would remain for a very long time, if he were not called away to fulfil
              his ordinary tasks.
                 It  happened  one  day  that  he  was  absent  from  breakfast,  from
              class, from the mid-day meal, and no one knew where he was; he was
              not in the study, nor in the dormitory. The Director was informed,
                                             51]]></page><page Index="64"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

          and he had a suspicion that he knew where to find him, namely in the
          church, as had happened before. He went to the church, and up into
          the choir near the sanctuary; there stood the boy like a statue; one
          foot was in front of the other, and one hand was on a book stand
          nearby,  while  the  other  was  on  his  breast.  His  face  was  turned
          towards the sanctuary and his gaze fixed on the tabernacle. His lips
          were not moving. The Director called him; no reply; he shook him
          gently; then he turned and said: "Oh, is the Mass over!" "See," said
          the priest, showing him his watch; "it is two o'clock." The boy said he
          was sorry for his transgression of the rule, and the Director sent him
          off to dinner, saying: "If anyone asks you where you have been, say
          that you have been carrying out an order of mine." This was in case
          any inquisitive boy should put inopportune questions to him.
             Another day, after making my usual thanksgiving, I was going out
          of the sacristy, when I heard a voice in the choir, as if someone were
          disputing.  I  went  in  to  see  what  was  the  matter,  and  found  Savio
          there. He  was  talking,  and  waiting  every now  and  again  as  though
          listening  to  the  answer.  Among  other  things  he  said,  I  distinctly
          caught the words: "Yes, oh my God, I have already said it, and I say
          so again: I love Thee and will love Thee till my last breath. If Thou
          knowest that I should ever offend Thee, let me die; yes, I would die
          rather than commit sin."
             I sometimes asked him what happened when he stayed behind like
          that.  He  would  answer  in  all  simplicity:  "I  become  distracted,  and
          losing  the  thread  of  my  prayers,  I  behold  such  beautiful  and
          entrancing sights that hours seem to go in a moment."
             One day he came to my room and said: "Come quickly, Father,
          come with me, there is a good work to be done."
             "Where am I to go," I said. "Make haste, make haste," he said. I
          hesitated, but as he insisted, and past experience had shown me the
          importance of such invitations, I went down with him. He went first,
          I followed. Down one street, then another, then a third, all in silence;
          there was yet another turning, and at a certain door he stopped; there
          he went up the stairs to the third floor, rang the bell vigorously, and
          turning to me said: "It is here that you are wanted." Then he went
          away.
             The door was opened and a woman appeared. "Oh, make haste,"
          she said, "quick, or it will be too late. My husband has abandoned his

                                         52]]></page><page Index="65"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO

              faith; now he is at the point of death and wishes to die a Catholic." I
              went over at once to the bedside, to the sick man, who was indeed
              very anxious to put the affairs of his soul in order. I did what I could
              for  the  man  without  loss  of  time,  and  his  confession  was  just
              completed, when the parish priest who had been sent for, arrived. He
              just  had  time  to  administer  Extreme  Unction  with  one  anointing,
              when the man breathed his last.
                 Afterwards I asked Dominic how he knew that there was a man ill
              at that house; he did not answer, but looked at me with an air of
              sadness, and I noticed that tears were beginning to come. I did not
              question him further.
                 Purity of life, love of God, and his longing for heavenly things had
              made  Dominic  almost  habitually  absorbed  in  God.  At  times,  even
              during  recreation,  these  visitations  would  occur  to  him.  He  would
              drop out of the game and walk away alone. Asked why he left his
              companions  he  would  answer:  "My  usual  distractions  are  assailing
              me;  it  seemed to  me that  Heaven opened  and  I  have  to  leave  my
              companions for fear that I should say something that would appear
              to them ridiculous."
                 On one occasion something was being said about the reward of
              the  innocent  souls.  Dominic  had  given  his  opinion,  and  by  the
              thought  of  such  things  he  was  quite  carried  away;  he  became
              motionless at first, then dropped into the arms of someone standing
              near. These ecstacies in fact came on in many different places, in the
              study, going to and from school, and even during class.
                 It  was  remarkable  that  he  often  spoke  about  the  Sovereign
              Pontiff, and expressed the desire of being able to see him, as he had
              something of great importance to tell him. As he had repeated this on
              several  occasions,  I  one  day  asked  him  what  the important  matter
              was. He replied: "If I could have an interview with the Pope, I would
              tell him, that in spite of the great tribulations which he has to endure
              at  present  he  should  never  slacken  in  his  particular  solicitude  for
              England: God is  preparing  a great triumph for Catholicism in that
              kingdom."
                 "Why, what grounds have you for that statement?"
                 "I will tell you, but do not mention it to others, for they might
              think it ridiculous. But if you go to Rome, tell Pius IX. for me. This is
              why  I  think  so.  One  morning,  during  my  thanksgiving  after

                                             53]]></page><page Index="66"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

          Communion, I had a repeated distraction, which was strange for me;
          I thought I saw a great stretch of country enveloped in a thick mist,
          and it was filled with a multitude of people. They were moving about,
          but  like  men,  who,  having  missed  their  way,  are  not  sure  of  their
          footing. Somebody near by said: 'This is England.' I was going to ask
          some questions about it when I saw His Holiness Pius IX. as I had
          seen him represented in pictures. He was majestically clad, and was
          carrying a shining torch with which he approached the multitude as if
          to enlighten their darkness. As he drew near, the light of the torch
          seemed  to  disperse  the  mist,  and  the  people  were  left  in  broad
          daylight.  'This  torch,'  said  my  informant,  'is  the  Catholic  religion
          which is to illuminate England.'"
             When I was in Rome in 1858 I related this to the Holy Father,
          who  was  greatly  interested  and  said:  "What  you  have  told  me
          confirms me in my resolution to do all that is possible for England,
          which has long been the object of my special care. What you have
          related is, to put it at its lowest estimation, the counsel of a devout
          soul."
             There  are  many  other  facts  of  a  somewhat  similar  nature,  but
          which are out of place in a small life like this. I have left them on
          record, so that, when, in the opinion of others, their publication is
          demanded, they maybe given to the world.




























                                         54]]></page><page Index="67"><![CDATA[CHAPTER XX
                     DOMINIC'S IDEAS ABOUT DYING AND HIS
                        PREPARATION FOR A HAPPY DEATH.

              T
                      HE brief years of Dominic's innocent life, as above related,
                      may well be considered as a continual preparation for death.
                      But he regarded the Sodality of the Immaculate Conception,
              which he had practically founded, as a secure means for obtaining the
              assistance of the Blessed Virgin, at the point of death, which many
              thought to be a not very remote contingency in Dominic's case. I do
              not know exactly whether he had a revelation concerning the time or
              circumstances of his death, or merely a presentiment of it, but it is
              certain that he spoke of it a good time before it occurred, and with
              such clearness and circumstantial knowledge, that it could not have
              been described more exactly by one who had actually witnessed his
              death.
                 On  account  of  the  state  of  his  health,  every  care  was  taken  to
              moderate his studies and his exercises of piety; but as an effect of his
              natural delicate build, and the constant spiritual effort, his strength
              gradually gave way. He had no misgivings about this himself, and had
              often said: "I must hurry, or else night will overtake me on the way,"
              which meant that he had only a short time left to him, and that he
              should use it well in the performance of good works.
                 It is the custom at the Oratory for the boys, to make the exercises
              for a good death every month. This consists chiefly in approaching
              the  Sacraments  of  Confession  and  Holy  Communion  as  though  it
              were to be for the last time. Pius IX. had granted several indulgences
                                             55]]></page><page Index="68"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

          to this pious  exercise. Dominic always made this preparation for a
          good death with an exactitude that could not be excelled. Among the
          prayers said in public on this day are an Our Father and Hail Mary for
          the  one  amongst  us  who  shall  be  the  first  to  die.  On  one  of  the
          monthly exercise days Dominic playfully said: "Instead of saying 'for
          the first one amongst us  who is  to die,' it ought rather to be: 'for
          Dominic Savio, who will be the first one amongst us to die.'" And
          this he remarked on more than one occasion.
             In  1856,  just  before  the  month  of  May  began,  he  went  to  his
          Director to ask for some special guidance in order to keep the month
          with particular devotion. The Director told him it should be done by
          the  most  exact  fulfilment  of  one's  duties,  by  receiving  Holy
          Communion daily, and performing some little act in honour of Our
          Lady every day. Dominic then wished to know what special grace he
          should ask for, and was told to ask that Our Lady might obtain for
          him  an  improvement  in  health,  and  the  grace  to  become  more
          pleasing in the sight of God. To this Dominic replied: "Yes, I shall
          ask  the  grace to become  a  saint, that she  may  help  me in the last
          moment of my life and that I may die a holy death."
             In fact during that month he seemed to be living only outwardly
          amongst  us  and  to  be  more  than  usually  in  communion  with  the
          world of angels; and his efforts to do something in honour of Our
          Lady  every  day  were  remarkably  successful,  so  much  so,  that  a
          companion was prompted to remark to him: "If you do so much this
          year, how will you be able to improve upon it next year?" Dominic
          replied: "You may leave that to me; I must do all that is possible this
          year, and if I am here next year, I will answer your question."
             In order that his failing health might have every care I arranged
          for  a  medical  consultation.  Dominic  was  examined  by  these
          specialists, and all wondered at his bright cheerfulness of disposition,
          the  acuteness  of  his  intellect,  and  the  prudence  displayed  in  his
          replies. Dr. Vallauri, of distinguished memory, who was one of the
          most eminent consulting physicians, said: "What a priceless treasure
          you have in this boy!"
             I asked him what was the cause of the boy's gradual decline, that
          could be noticed almost day by day. He said it was the delicacy of his
          constitution,  his  precocious  knowledge,  and  the  constant  highly
          strung tension of his whole being; these were too great a strain on his

                                         56]]></page><page Index="69"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO

              vital powers.
                 "Is there any remedy that you can suggest?"
                 "The best remedy, as far as I can see, is to let him go to Paradise,
              for which he seems  to be quite ready; but the only thing  that can
              prolong his life is to make him put his studies entirely aside, and let
              him have some light occupation suitable to his strength."























































                                             57]]></page><page Index="70"><![CDATA[CHAPTER XXI
             DOMINIC'S INTEREST IN THE SICK. HE HAD TO
               LEAVE THE ORATORY FOR CHANGE OF AIR.
                             HIS PARTING WORDS.

          D
                   OMINIC'S gradual decline was not so rapid or so marked
                   as  to  cause  him  to  be  continually  in  bed;  he  sometimes
                   went into the class room, or the study, or helped in some
          light domestic work, as the doctor had suggested; but his chief delight
          was to attend on his sick companions whenever there chanced to be
          any. But he seemed to derive such pleasure from it that he doubted
          whether it could be meritorious in the sight of God.
             However,  while  he  waited  upon  their  needs  he  was  particularly
          pleased to be able to assist them in some spiritual way, and was very
          skillful in his method of so doing. He remarked to one companion
          that the poor body could not last forever, so that it had to become
          weak some time or other and gradually be consumed; but then the
          soul which had been set free would go to its everlasting home, and
          enjoy an eternal happiness. If the medicine were distasteful, he would
          remark to the sick boy that it was not nearly as bad as the gall and
          vinegar of our Divine Lord, and that it was  ordained by God that
          these remedies should be provided for the body.
             Dominic's own health had already made it evident that he would
          have to leave the Oratory and go home for his native air. He had a
          great repugnance to this, for it interrupted his practices of piety; and
          in  fact  I  had  sent  him  to  his  home  just  before  this,  but  he  only
          remained there a few days and then returned to the Oratory. I must
                                         58]]></page><page Index="71"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO

              own  that  our  regret  was  mutual  and  I  would  have  made  every
              sacrifice to keep him amongst us; I regarded him with the affection
              that  a  father  has  towards  the  best  beloved  of  his  sons.  But  the
              recommendations  of  the  doctors  made  it  clear  that  it  would  be
              against all prudence to keep him longer at the Oratory, especially as
              he had been troubled with a severe and obstinate cough for some
              days.
                 Notice  was  accordingly  sent  to  his  father  and  the  day  for  his
              departure was fixed for March 1st, 1857. In order to make a sacrifice
              of his will to God, Dominic submitted to this arrangement, for he
              would have much rather ended his days at the Oratory. Somebody
              suggested to him that it would not be for long, and that he would
              return quite well and be able to continue his studies. But Dominic
              was  under no misapprehension; he replied that he was  going  away
              and he knew quite well that he would never return.
                 On  the  evening  before  his  departure  he  stayed  with  me  a  long
              time, so much so that he had no wish to leave me. He had a great
              many questions to ask, concerning chiefly his own method of action
              as an invalid, which now he was, and how he might make that state
              meritorious. I told him that he should offer his illness and his life to
              God. He was anxious about his past faults and whether I thought he
              would  be  saved.  I  assured  him  that  whatever  he  might  have
              committed  was  forgiven,  and  that  he  need  have  no  fear  of  being
              saved.  In  regard  to  temptations,  I  counselled  him  to  reply  to  the
              tempter that he  had  already  given  his  soul  to  Our  Lord,  who had
              redeemed it with His Precious Blood.
                 He had many further questions  about dying  and about Heaven,
              and  he  seemed  like  one  who  had  his  foot  upon  the  threshold  of
              Heaven and wanted to know beforehand what it was like.
                 The day for his departure happened to be the day for the exercises
              of a happy death, and these he made with the utmost fervour. In fact
              I have no words in which to describe the devotion with which he
              approached  the  Sacraments,  though  it  made  a  deep  impression on
              me. He regarded these exercises as his actual preparation for death,
              and thought that perhaps his end might come at any moment.
                 His few preparations for departure were soon made, though they
              were  carried  out  with  that  scrupulous  care  which  showed  that  he
              regarded them as the last acts he would do at the Oratory. He went

                                             59]]></page><page Index="72"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

          to each of his companions to say goodbye, and to several he gave a
          little  message  of  advice  or  encouragement  or  recommendation.  To
          one boy he owed a few pence. He called to him and said: "Come let
          us  put  our  accounts  right,  or  else  there may  be  trouble  in  settling
          accounts  with  God."  To  his  associates  in  the  Confraternity  of  the
          Immaculate  Conception  he  had  some  special  advice  to  give,  and
          encouraged them always to have the greatest confidence in Our Lady.
             When he was going he turned to me and said: "Then you will not
          have my body with you, and I must needs take it to Mondonio? It
          would  have  been  but  a  brief  inconvenience  and  then  all  would  be
          over . . . . But the Will of God be done. If you go to Rome do not
          forget the message I have given you concerning England; pray that I
          may have a happy death, and that we may see  each other again in
          Heaven.
             We had reached the door of the Oratory leading out to the street.
          He still had hold of my hand, but he turned to his companions and
          said: "Goodbye, my friends, pray for me, and may we meet again in
          Heaven where there are no more partings." Just as he was leaving he
          said to me: "I would like a present as a souvenir." I asked him what
          he would prefer to have, a book for example?" No, something better
          than that." I thought perhaps he wanted something for his journey
          and suggested it to him. He replied: "Yes, it is exactly that, something
          for the journey to eternity. You have spoken of a plenary indulgence
          from the Pope, for those who are dying; I should like to participate in
          that."
             I said I would willingly insert his name amongst those who should
          enjoy that privilege which I had obtained especially from Rome.
             Thus he left the Oratory where he had spent the last three years.
          They had been three happy years for the boy, three years of continual
          edification for his companions and even for his superiors; he had left
          it now to return no more.
             His parting salutations, so unusual in a boy, had astonished all of
          us. We knew that he suffered a good deal from his illness, but as he
          was nearly always up and about, we were not accustomed to regard it
          as causing immediate anxiety. His cheerful disposition also went far
          to  conceal  his  sufferings.  Therefore,  although  we  were  inclined  to
          take his parting words seriously, and were greatly grieved at them, we
          still had hopes that he would return and continue his studies. But the

                                         60]]></page><page Index="73"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO

              sequel proved otherwise. He was ready for Heaven; during the few
              years of his boyhood he had merited the reward of the just, and it
              seemed that God designed to take him to Himself in the spring time
              of his life, and before he should encounter those dangers which bring
              shipwreck often even to the purest souls.
























































                                             61]]></page><page Index="74"><![CDATA[CHAPTER XXII
           THE PROGRESS OF HIS ILLNESS. HE RECEIVES THE
                LAST SACRAMENTS. EDIFYING INCIDENTS.

          D
                   OMINIC had left the Oratory on the 1st of March. The
                   journey  home  in  the  carriage  and  the  change  of  scene
                   appeared to do him good, and therefore it was not thought
          necessary  that  he  should  remain  in  bed.  But  after  a  few  days  he
          seemed  to  become  weaker,  his  appetite  was  poor,  and  his  cough
          more noticeable, so that the doctor was consulted. His opinion was
          that the boy was a great deal worse than he appeared. He had him put
          to bed at once, and as he thought there was some inflamation he had
          recourse to blood letting.
             This remedy usually had great terrors for the young. The doctor
          therefore advised Dominic to fix his attention on something else, and
          to have patience and courage. The boy smiled and said: "What is such
          a little wound compared to those made by the nails in the hands and
          feet of our Saviour?" Then with the greatest tranquility of mind, in
          almost a playful mood, and without the least sign of apprehension, he
          watched  the  whole  operation.  When  it  had  been  repeated  several
          times  he  seemed  to  be  somewhat  better; the  doctor thought there
          was a turn towards improvement; his parents thought likewise; but
          Dominic  was  not  to  be  brought  to  their  opinion.  Guided  by  the
          thought that it is better to receive the Sacraments in good time, than
          to delay till it was too late, he sent for his father and said: "Father, I
          think it would be better to consult the heavenly physician. I wish to
          go to Confession and Communion."
                                         62]]></page><page Index="75"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO

                 His parents quite thought that he was on the road to recovery; it
              was with sorrow they heard such remarks as these, and it was just to
              satisfy his desire that they sent for the priest. He came at once, heard
              the boy's confession and, in accordance with his request, brought the
              Holy Viaticum.
                 The devotion and eager fervour displayed by Dominic under these
              circumstances  is  better  imagined  than  described.  Whenever  he
              approached the Sacraments it was in the attitude and dispositions of a
              Saint Aloysius, and now that he received them for what he deemed to
              be the last time, it was with outbursts of ardent love that his heart
              went out to meet his Divine Lord.
                 He  recalled  then  the  promises  he  had  made  at  his  First
              Communion: how he had besought Jesus and Mary to be his constant
              friends, and resolved to prefer death rather than wilfully give way to
              sin. When his thanksgiving was over he said in complete tranquility:
              "Now I am at peace; it is true that I have to make the long journey to
              eternity, but with our Divine Lord by my side, I have nothing to fear;
              tell everyone that if they have Him there is nothing to fear, not even
              death itself."
                 Dominic had always been a model of patience under suffering, but
              this virtue was even more conspicuous in him during his last illness,
              which  he  bore  as  a  Saint.  Whatever  he  could  do  for  himself,  he
              wished still to do, so as not to inconvenience anyone; he thought his
              parents had already had too much to bear from him. He took any and
              every medicine without the least sign of distaste, and underwent ten
              times the operation of blood letting without any sign of impatience.
                 After  four  days  of  attendance  the  doctor  congratulated the boy
              and his parents on the improvement he found, and told the mother
              and  father  to  thank  God  that  now  the  worst  was  over,  and  only
              convalescence remained.
                 The parents were naturally pleased; but Dominic smiled and said:
              "The  world  is  overcome.  I  have  now  only  to  make  a  befitting
              appearance before God."
                 When the doctor had gone, Dominic seemed to place no reliance
              on his promise of recovery, and asked that the Sacrament of Extreme
              Unction might be administered to him. In this again the parents only
              complied in order to satisfy him, for neither they nor the priest could
              perceive any signs of his being near to death; the very serenity of his

                                             63]]></page><page Index="76"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

          countenance,  and  his  bright  conversation,  made  them  believe  that
          there was really some improvement.
             But whether Dominic was guided by sentiments of devotion, or
          whether  some  divinely  inspired  voice  had  spoken to his  heart, the
          fact  is  that  he  counted  the  days  and  hours  of  his  life  as  a  person
          reckons numbers in arithmetic, and every moment was occupied in
          preparation to appear before God. Before receiving Extreme Unction
          he expressed his devotion thus: "Pardon my sins, O God, for I love
          Thee,  and  wish  to  love  Thee  for  ever!  May  this  Sacrament  which
          Thou permitted me to receive in Thy infinite mercy, blot out all the
          sins I have committed by my hearing, sight, tongue, hands and feet;
          may  my  body  and  soul  be  sanctified  through  the  merits  of  Thy
          passion. Amen."
             He answered all the responses in such a clear voice, and with such
          realisation of their meaning, that one would have imagined him to be
          in perfect health. It was then the 9th of March, the fourth day of his
          illness, and the last day of his life. His strength was diminishing, and
          remedies seemed to have no effect, so that the Papal Blessing  was
          given. He said the Confiteor himself, and responded to the priest in his
          turn. When he was told that it earned with it a Plenary Indulgence, he
          showed the greatest joy and said Deo gratias et semper Deo gratias. Then
          he  turned  to  the  Crucifix  and  recited  some  verses  of  a  favourite
          hymn.


























                                         64]]></page><page Index="77"><![CDATA[CHAPTER XXIII
                      HIS LAST MOMENTS AND HOLY DEATH.

              I
                   T is one of the maxims of our Faith that at the hour of death
                   we reap the fruit of our good works during life: Quae seminaverit
                   homo, haec et metet. However, it sometimes happens  that good,
              pious  people  experience  fear  and  dread  at  the  approach  of  death.
              This is in accordance with the adorable decrees of God, who wishes
              to purify those souls from the small stains they may have contracted,
              so that they may increase their merit in heaven.
                 It was not thus with Dominic Savio. It is my conviction that God
              deigned to give him the hundredfold, which He bestows upon the
              souls of the just, as a preliminary to the glory of Paradise. And indeed
              the innocence which he preserved to the last moment of his life, his
              generous Faith, his habit of constant prayer, his mortifications, and
              the sufferings which had, as it were, beset his life, certainly merited
              that consolation for him at the hour of death.
                 Hence  it  was  that  he  perceived  his  end  approaching  with  the
              tranquility of an innocent soul; it would seem that he did not feel
              even the suffering and oppressiveness which are a natural outcome of
              the efforts of the soul to break the bonds by which it is united to the
              body.  In  short,  Savio's  death  was  more  like  the  passing  into  a
              peaceful slumber.
                 By the evening of March 9th he had received all the consolations
              of our Holy Religion. Anyone listening to his voice, or noticing his
              cheerful countenance, would have thought he was lying in bed for a
              little rest. His brightmanner, his looks, still full of life, the complete
                                             65]]></page><page Index="78"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

          possession  of  his  senses,  quite  astonished  everyone,  and  nobody,
          except himself, believed him to be on the point of death.
             An hour and a half before he passed away, the parish priest came
          to see him, and seeing how calm he was, he was surprised to hear
          him  recommending  his  soul  to  God.  He  continued  to  make
          aspirations and short ejaculations expressing his desire to go speedily
          to heaven.
             The priest remarked: "I am at a loss to know what to suggest for
          the recommendation of a soul of this sort."
             He recited some prayers, and was about to leave, when Dominic
          asked him for some final thought by way of souvenir. The priest said
          he could recommend nothing to him but the thought of the Sacred
          Passion; Dominic thanked him for this and continued to recall it, and
          to repeat invocations to Jesus and Mary. Then he rested for about
          half an hour.
             At the end of that time he turned to his parents and said: "Father,
          it is time."
             The father replied: "I am here, my son, what would you like?"
             "It is time, father; get my prayer book, and read the prayers for a
          good death."
             At these words the mother began to weep, and had to go out of
          the room. The father was greatly moved, but he restrained his grief so
          as to read the prayers. Dominic repeated them after him, and, in the
          proper place, said by himself: "Merciful Jesus, have mercy on me."
          When they came to the part which says: "But deign to receive me
          into Thy Kingdom where I may for ever sing Thy praises," Dominic
          added: "Yes, that is exactly what I desire; to sing the praises of God
          for  all  eternity."  He  now  seemed  to  rest  a  moment,  as  though
          pondering  over  something  in  his  mind.  Then  he  opened  his  eyes
          again,  and  said  with  a  clear  voice,  and  a  smiling  countenance:
          "Goodbye, father, goodbye; the priest wanted to tell me something
          else, but I cannot remember it now.... Oh! what a beautiful sight I
          behold ...." Thus saying, with his hands joined, and a heavenly smile,
          his soul passed away.
             Yes, go forth, faithful soul, to meet thy Creator; Heaven is opened
          to thee, and the angels and saints are rejoicing for thee; Jesus, whom
          you loved so much, invites you and says: "Come, good and faithful
          servant, thou hast fought and won the victory, come and enjoy that

                                         66]]></page><page Index="79"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO

              happiness which will never fail: Intra in gaudium Domini tui."































































                                             67]]></page><page Index="80"><![CDATA[CHAPTER XXIV
                          THE NEWS OF HIS DEATH.
                          REMARKABLE TESTIMONY.

          T
                 HE  last  words  uttered  by  Dominic,  as  related  in  the
                 preceding chapter, did not give his father the impression that
                 he was  dying, He thought he was  again falling into a brief
          period of repose. He went out of the room for a few minutes, and on
          his  return  spoke  to  Dominic;  but  there  was  no  reply,  and  he
          perceived  that  he  had  really  expired.  The  grief  of  the  parents  and
          their desolation at the loss of such a son may be well imagined.
             News  was  most  anxiously  awaited  at  the  Oratory.  A  letter  was
          dispatched to me in haste by his father, and when I read: "I have sad
          news  for  you,"  I  concluded  that  all  was  over.  He  went  on  to  say:
          "Our  dear  son,  your  pupil,  gave  up  his  soul  to  God  yesterday
          evening,  with  the  innocence  of  another  St.  Aloysius,  and  after
          receiving the Holy Sacrament in a most edifying manner."
             There  was  consternation  at  the  Oratory  when  I  told  the  boys.
          Some were in grief at the loss of such a true friend; others, at being
          deprived of a valuable adviser, and all missed the inspiring example
          of his virtuous life. Some gathered together to say a prayer for him,
          but the greater number declared that they were sure he was a saint
          and  already  in  Paradise.  Some  began  immediately  to  invoke  his
          intercession, and there was a general endeavour to get something that
          had  belonged  to  him,  as  a  relic.  The  master  of  the  class  that  he
          attended  in  Turin,  Father  Picco,  announced  the  sad  tidings  to  his
          boys in these words:
                                         68]]></page><page Index="81"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO


                 "A  short  time  ago,  I  happened  to  speak  to  you  about  the
              uncertainty  of  human  life,  and  I  pointed  out  that  death  does  not
              spare  even  those  who  are  in  the  spring  time  of  youth.  On  that
              occasion, I had an example in one of the boys, who had been a pupil
              of this very class, a boy full of life and vigour, and yet after a few days
              absence we heard that he had been taken ill and had passed away, to
              the great sorrow of his parents and relations.
                 "When I brought forward that example I little thought that this
              year would be saddened by a similar occurrence, that such an instance
              would be repeated in the case of one who was sitting here listening to
              me. Death has carried off one of your companions, Dominic Savio.
              You may remember that he was not very well when he was here last,
              and then had to stay away from the classes altogether. The doctors
              advised his removal to his native place, and there he died after only
              four days of illness.
                 "Yesterday I read the letter from his father in which he makes the
              sad  announcement,  and  the  picture  he  draws  of  the  boy's  saintly
              death moved me to tears. He could find no more suitable expression
              to  apply  to his  beloved  son  than  to  call him  another  St. Aloysius,
              both  on  account  of  the  holiness  of  his  life  and  his  resignation  in
              death. I leave to his superiors at the Oratory to describe the holiness
              of  his  life,  the intensity  of  his  fervour  and  piety;  I  must  allow  his
              companions  and  friends,  who  were  in  daily  contact  with  him,  to
              describe  the  gentleness  and  modesty  of  his  demeanour,  and  the
              careful restraint he exercised over his words. As far as he came under
              my direction he always deserved the highest praise for his behaviour,
              his  diligence  and  exactness,  and  it  would  afford  me  the  greatest
              consolation if all of you would resolve to follow his example.
                 "While he was  at the Oratory, but had not yet begun to attend
              these  classes,  his  diligence  and  piety  won  for  him  the  highest
              reputation. So rapid was his progress that I was most anxious for him
              to come, and I had the highest possible hopes for his future career. I
              had met him sometimes in my visits to the Oratory, had been struck
              by  the  innocence  of  his  life  and  the  winning  gentleness  of  his
              disposition,  and  had  been  drawn  to  him  in  a  particular  manner.
              During  the  time  that  he  attended  these  classes  he  fulfilled  my
              expectations  perfectly, and all of you are witnesses  to his  excellent

                                             69]]></page><page Index="82"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

          conduct.  In  many  details,  which  most  boys  consider  beneath  their
          notice, he was scrupulously exact, and by the fervour and recollection
          he brought to all his actions, he sanctified his whole day and made it
          an acceptable offering in the sight of God. Such conduct is worthy of
          imitation; it would bring consolation to parents and teachers, and all
          blessings and happiness to the boys themselves.
             "Dominic gave us an example of how a life should be spent in the
          service  of  God,  in  contrast  to  those  youths  who  seem  to  be  in
          ignorance of the end for which they were created, or who stifle the
          good dispositions that come to every soul. Reflect on the example of
          Savio, and it will help you to spend your life in the service of your
          Creator and to be prepared to give an account when the time comes.
          If I notice an improvement in work and behaviour, I shall regard it as
          obtained by the intercession of Dominic, and as a reward for having
          been associated with him, if only for a short time."
             Thus  did  Fr.  Picco  announce  the  death  of  one  of  his  most
          promising pupils, and evince the general sorrow at his loss.




































                                         70]]></page><page Index="83"><![CDATA[CHAPTER XXV
                     THE INFLUENCE OF DOMINIC'S VIRTUES.
                   FAVOURS RECEIVED. A RECOMMENDATION.

              E
                       VEN after such a brief description of his life, it will not be
                       surprising that God deigned to honour his servant, Dominic
                       Savio, with special marks of honour, which made his virtues
              shine  forth  the  brighter.  During  his  life  many  had  depended  for
              guidance on his advice, and been encouraged by his example; others
              had recommended their intentions to his prayers, and they had often
              been  answered  in  a  striking  manner.  It  was  natural,  therefore, that
              after his death confidence in his intercession should rapidly spread.
                 As  soon  as  the  news  of  his  death  reached  us,  many  of  his
              companions went about openly proclaiming him to be a saint. When
              the  usual  prayers  were  being  offered  for  him,  and  the  Litany  was
              recited, they did not think it necessary or proper to say: "Pray for
              him"; but continued the customary: "Pray for us." Dominic has gone
              to heaven, they said, and can need no payers from us.
                 Others said: "If Dominic, with his innocent life and good works,
              has not gone to Heaven, who will ever get there?" Thus it was that by
              degrees he became a regular model for the example of all, and was
              regarded as a powerful protector and intercessor in Heaven. Almost
              every  day  I  received  accounts  of  temporal  and  spiritual  graces
              received. Illnesses were cured, sometimes immediately. I myself was a
                                                           1
              witness of an instantaneous cure of yellow fever.

              1  This confidence in the intercession of Dominic  was greatly increased by an
                                             71]]></page><page Index="84"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

             I have before me many documents containing accounts of favours
          received through Dominic's intercession. The character and authority
          of the writers are beyond question; but as most of them are still alive,
          I shall not insert them for the present. There is one related here of a
          grace  obtained  by  a  student  who  had  been  a  companion  of
          Dominic's.
             In the year 1858, this young man's health became very precarious.
          In  fact  it  had  broken  down  so  badly,  that  he  had  to  interrupt  his
          course  of philosophy, take every precaution, and at the end of the
          year he could not present himself for examination. However, there
          was a later examination towards the end of the year, and he thought
          he might be able to prepare for that, and thus prevent the loss of a
          whole year in the course of his studies; but his health continued to
          decline and his hopes gradually died away.
             During the autumn vacation he had a change of air and rest, and
          this  seemed  to  give  him  renewed  strength,  so  that  he  returned  to
          Turin and applied himself to his studies. But again his health broke
          down, and he was in a worse state than ever, so that he saw there was
          no possibility of application to study, or of taking an examination.
             "It was then," he says, "that the accounts of the favours obtained
          by Dominic Savio struck me particularly, and I determined to make a
          novena  to  obtain  the  assistance  of  this  former  associate  of  mine.
          Certain  prayers  were  said  daily,  and  I  made  a  special  appeal  on
          account of my previous  intimacy with him, we having  been in the


          assertion  made  is  the  strongest  terms  by  his  father.  He  says:  "I  was  in  the
          greatest affliction at the loss of my son, and was consumed by a desire to know
          what was his position in the other world. God deigned to comfort me. About a
          month after his death, during a very restless night, I saw, as it were, the ceiling
          opened,  and  Dominic  appeared  in  the  midst  of  dazzling  light.  I  was  beside
          myself  at  this  sight,  and  cried  out:  "O  Dominic,  my  son,  are  you  already  in
          Paradise?" "Yes," he replied, "I am in Heaven." Then pray for your brothers and
          sisters, and your mother and father, that we may all come to join you one day
          is Heaven." "Yes, yes, I will pray," was the answer. "Then he disappeared, and
          the room became as before." This the father asserts to be the simple truth.


                                         72]]></page><page Index="85"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO

              same class, and striving for the first place.
                 "About the fifth day, my health was suddenly much better, and I
              immediately took to my books; I seemed to master the subjects with
              great ease and took the examination. Nor was it a short-lived favour,
              for my health has since remained perfect, and two months have now
              elapsed  since  I  was  ill.  I  cannot  but  recognise  that  this  grace  was
              obtained  from  God  by  the  intercession  of  my  companion  and
              friend."
                 With this fact I shall bring the life of Dominic Savio to a close. In
              an appendix other favours are related, which seem to be conducive to
              the glory of God and the good of souls.
                 But,  dear  Reader,  before  parting,  I  should  like  to  propose  some  little
              resolution, which may be of service to you and to myself and to others; I should
              like you to join with me to a resolution to imitate young Savio in the practice of
              the virtues which are compatible with our state. In his own position he lived a
              most happy, virtuous and innocent life, which was crowned by a holy death. If we
              imitate  his  manner  of  life,  we  shall  be  assured  of  being  like  him  in  our  last
              moments.
                 But  he  is  chiefly  worthy  of  imitation  in  frequenting  the  Sacrament  of
              Confession, which was his support in the constant practice of virtue, his guiding
              star through life, and his consolation at the hour of death. Frequent and devout
              use should be made of this sacrament so condusive to salvation; but every time we
              do so, let us give a thought to our last confession, in order to make sure that it has
              been properly made, and when there is need for so doing we should apply remedies
              to the defects. It seems to me that this is the safest means to spend happy days in
              the midst of the troubles of life, at the end of which we shall calmly await the
              moment of death.
                 Then, with our minds at rest, and a smile on our lips, we shall go forth to
              meet our Divine Lord who will graciously welcome us; and, judging us according
              to His great M ercy, will lead us both, I trust, dear reader, from the trials of this
              life to a happy eternity.












                                             73]]></page><page Index="86"><![CDATA[APPENDIX.
           CERTAIN GRACES OBTAINED FROM GOD THROUGH
                 THE INTERCESSION OF DOMINIC SAVIO.

          A
                  MONGST  the  many  graces  which  are  attributed  to  the
                  intercession of Dominic Savio I select some which are of a
                  more ordinary nature.
             Of these graces there exist at the Archiepiscopal Palace at Turin
          an  authentic  account,  signed  by  the  recipients  of  the  heavenly
          favours, for the truth of which they have publicly vouched. In order
          that  the  account  may  be  given  with  greater  exactness  and
          truthfulness, I have deemed it advisable to give the facts just as they
          are related in the authentic accounts above-mentioned. They are as
          follows:

                        CURE OF A MALIGNANT FEVER.

          If it be the duty of a Christian to keep hidden such facts as redound
          to his own honour, it is, on the other hand, his duty to manifest such
          things as serve to glorify God's servants and to exalt His Holy Name
          before men.
              This duty it is that impels me to publish a fact concerning the
          servant of God, Dominic Savio, whom I recognise as my protector
          before God and the benefactor of my family.
              I  had  recommended  myself  on  several  occasions  to  the  pious
          Louis Comollo, as others had done, and God in His goodness had
          always answered my request; on many occasions also I recommended


                                         74]]></page><page Index="87"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO


              myself to Dominic Savio, and his intercession with Our Lord on my
              behalf was always efficacious. Private motives keep me from relating
              a number of facts; one however I must make known, both in order to
              give  to  God  that  honour  which  is  His  due,  and  to  glorify  before
              Christians  the faithful servant, whom God Himself has  deigned to
              make the depository of His treasures.
                  Here is the fact in question; in relating it I am only saying what is
              absolutely true, and conscientiously stated.
                  On the 8th September, 1858, I caught a severe chill, which after
              keeping  me  confined  to  my  bed  for  some  weeks,  developed  into
              fever.
                  I  tried  the  various  treatments  prescribed  by  the  doctors,  but
              without avail. My delicate constitution and my weak state of health
              soon  brought  me  to  a  state  of  great  weakness  and  left  me  almost
              prostrate.
                  Visits from medical men, consultations, change of air, medicines,
              country, were all unavailing in my case. To my bodily ailments was
              added anxiety of mind, consequent on my inability to attend to my
              duty as a mother of a family. I was indeed unfortunate. Prostrate on a
              sick  bed,  all  hopes  in  doctors  and  medicines  gone,  nothing  now
              remained  for  me  but  help  from  Heaven,  and  this  did not  fail  me.
              Only a few days before, a small book containing the life of Dominic
              Savio  had  been  published,  and  moved  by  the  virtues  which  he
              practised during life, and still more by the graces which others had
              obtained through his intercession, I resolved to recommend myself to
              him in order to obtain relief in my distress.
                  On the night, therefore, of February 20th, 1859, relying on the
              power  of  God,  who  grants  His  favours  in  abundance  through  the
              intercession of those who have been faithful to Him in life, urged on
              likewise  by  the  need of  comfort  in  my  afflictions  and  relief  in  my
              infirmities, I gave utterance to the following words: "O thou, who in
              a few years  of life didst attain to so high a degree of virtue, show
              forth the power and goodness of God; let me know that thou art in
                                             75]]></page><page Index="88"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO

          heaven and that from that happy place thou dost protect thy clients.
          Obtain from God that I may be relieved of my infirmities and may
          recover  my  former  state  of  health.  I  promise  that  I  will  relate,
          whenever I am able, the favour which thou wilt obtain for me from
          God." I had hardly finished these last words, when I felt a sort of
          shivering  through  my  whole  body.  I  felt at  once  a  great  relief;  my
          infirmities  vanished,  the  fever  disappeared  and  a  sweet  sleep  stole
          upon me, so that I was able to spend that night in calm repose. In the
          morning I was perfectly cured. Dr. Frola, who came to see me, was
          not a little astonished at so great an improvement. "I do not know,"
          he  said,  "what  remedy  has  been  able  to  do  you  so  much  good.
          Certainly the finger of God has been here."
              I got up from my bed and found myself in perfect health, after a
          sickness  which  should  have  required  some  months  at  least  of
          convalescence.
              Eight months have elapsed since my cure, and up to the present,
          thank  God,  through  the  intercession  of  that  holy  youth,  Dominic
          Savio, I have not been subject to ailments of any sort. All this that I
          have  of  my  own  accord  here  set  down,  I  desire  to  be  published
          wherever it may be deemed to promote the greater glory of God and
          the good of souls: and I am prepared to testify to the truth of the
          same in the presence of any person whatsoever. I have subsequently
          on various  occasions  had recourse  to this heavenly benefactor and
          have always been heard. May these facts serve to strengthen the faith
          of other faithful Christians, so that they may have recourse  to this
          source of blessings; and may they find in their spiritual and temporal
          needs effectual help in him, who lived a holy life on earth, and now in
          his glory protects us from heaven.

                                                 COUNTESS BUSCHETTI
                                                           née di Mazzenile.
          (Turin, 15 October, 1859.)



                                         76]]></page><page Index="89"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO


                          CURE OF A SERIOUS EYE COMPLAINT.

                 It  was  in  1858,  about  the  end  of  May,  that  my  eyes  became
              seriously  affected,  and  the  pain  continued,  sometimes  diminishing,
              sometimes increasing, up to the November of 1859. Beginning from
              the month of March of that year it increased to such an extent that I
              was from the very outset constrained to lay aside all studies, and later
              on to give them up altogether. In the early part of July my affliction
              had increased to such an extent, that college life, which I had before
              enjoyed, now appeared to me to be unbearable.
                 Thus it came about, that, owing to the state of my eyes, and the
              regret  I  felt  at  the  sight  of  my  companions  working  for  the
              approaching  examinations,  I  had  to  go  home:  I  thought  some
              improvement might follow, and indeed I did get slightly better, but
              only for a short time. Four or five days had scarcely elapsed from the
              time the improvement set in, when the malady again took a turn for
              the worse, and I was not merely reduced to my former state, but to a
              far more deplorable one. I then had recourse to several doctors. One
              of them required me to take about 400 pills of some particular make;
              I took them as prescribed and followed minutely the directions given
              me, but all to no effect. I was bled four times, but without avail. On
              five  occasions  I  submitted  to  blistering  operations  behind the  ears
              without  deriving  any  benefit  thereby.  I  was  at  this  time  visited  by
              other well known eye specialists, amongst others  Cavaliere Sperim,
              Dr.  Fissore  and  Dr.  Paganini,  but,  after  submitting  me  to  various
              tests, they told me plainly that the way to cure the disease with which
              I was afflicted was still to them an unknown problem.
                 Weary, then, at my hopeless plight I knew not where to turn. My
              days  were  spent  continually  in  a  dark  room.  All  amusement  was  a
              source  of  horror  to  me  and  my  eyes  had  become  abnormally
              inflamed.  Towards  the  end  of  October  I  seemed  to  feel  some
              improvement, and, with the hope of a speedy and complete cure  l
              returned  to  the  college.  A  fortnight,  however,  had  hardly  elapsed
              when my eyes  again began to give me so much trouble that I felt
              doubtful  of  ever  being  able  to  study  again.  I  then  had  my  arms
              blistered and the operation was subsequently repeated; the same was
              done several times to my ears, but no benefit resulted. I often spoke
              to the Director of the House about it, and he, in order to console me,
                                             77]]></page><page Index="90"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO


          would  address  to  me  such  words  as  he  knew  would  be  to  my
          temporal and spiritual advantage, encouraging me to be patient, and
          holding out hopes of a speedy recovery.
             One  evening,  whilst  all  the  boys  were  engaged  in  some  singing
          classes, I was sitting thoughtful and sad, with my face buried in my
          hands, and leaning on the table near which the Director was seated.
          Presently he arose, and coming quietly up to me, touched me on the
          shoulder, smiling as he did so, and spoke to me as follows: "Why can
          we not free you, once and for all, from this trouble? I wish to see the
          end of it. Let us endeavour to take possession of Dominic Savio and
          not allow him to depart until he has obtained your cure?" At these
          words  I  looked  at  him  steadfastly,  but  said  nothing.  Then  he
          continued: "Yes, pray every day during this novena (it was the eve of
          the  first  day  of  the  novena  for  the  feast  of  the  Immaculate
          Conception)  to  Dominic  Savio,  that  he  may  intercede  for  you.
          Endeavour to be in such a state as to be able to go to Communion
          every day of this novena. In the evening, before retiring to bed, say
          these words: "Dominic Savio, pray for me," and add one 'Hail Mary.'"
          I  promised  to  do  this  exactly,  upon  which  he  continued:  "That  is
          right, do what I have told you and I will remember you every day of
          this  novena  in  the  Holy  Mass."  "And  who  knows,"  he  added,
          "whether this time Dominic Savio will succeed in escaping us before
          you have been cured."
             On  the  very  day  that  I  began  to  make  the  novena  I  felt  an
          improvement in my malady. I then continued the practices of piety
          with greater fervour, and was soon rewarded for doing so, for in a
          few days my eyes were completely cured. During the novena I had
          promised  that,  if,  after  a  certain  time,  I  had  no  further  relapse,  I
          would do my best to have published, in honour of Dominic Savio,
          the grace I had received from him.
             I now keep my promise, for the time fixed (1st February, 1860)
          has elapsed and I am in perfect health. I hope that Dominic Savio
          will continue to bestow his favours upon me, and I on my part shall
          do all that I can to show my gratitude to him, striving to imitate him
          in those virtues of which he gave such a striking example. Meanwhile
          let praise be rendered to God and to Dominic Savio, through whose
          special protection I obtained this grace.
             (Turin, 1st February, 1860).
                                         78]]></page><page Index="91"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO


                 Thank God, my eyes are still in a perfectly healthy condition, and I
              hereby confirm the above statement.

                                              EDWARD DONATA, of Saluggia.
                 (Turin, March 20th, 1861).


                        INSTANTANEOUS CURE OF TOOTHACHE.

                 Having read the life of the holy youth Dominic Savio I conceived
              a deep veneration for him.
                 But a fact worthy of notice  - a fact which has made me deeply
              indebted  to  this  heavenly  Protector,  is  the  one  I  am  about  to  set
              down, with the request that you will give it that publicity which you
              may think fit. On the morning of Thursday, the 7th of April of the
              present year (1859) I had a slight attack of headache. I paid no heed
              to it, thinking it was only a passing indisposition, but it increased as
              the  day  went  on,  so  that  I  was  unable  to  work  or  to  sleep  the
              following  night.  On  getting  up  on  Friday,  with  the  pain  ever
              increasing, I was seized with such a sharp attack of toothache that
              although  I  went  to  class  I  could  neither  study  nor  attend  to  the
              explanations  given,  nor  to  anything  else,  so  severe  was  the  pain  I
              experienced. The trouble went on increasing until, in the evening, in
              sheer desperation, I was seized with a fit of uncontrollable weeping.
              It was time for the evening class and I was wandering aimlessly about
              the house, a prey to racking pain, when the prefect met me on the
              balcony  overlooking  the  playground.  "Recommend  yourself  to
              Dominic Savio," he said to me, for he understood the cause of my
              trouble. "Recommend yourself to Dominic Savio; he can cure you if
              he wishes to do so." I thanked him for this advice and reproached
              myself for not having thought about it sooner. I hastened at once to
              Our Lady's altar, knelt down on the step which had so often been
              hallowed by the presence of Savio, when he used to withdraw to the
              silence of the sanctuary, his heart filled with devotion towards her, by
              whose aid he succeeded in attaining  the love, zeal and piety which
              now form a crown of glory for him in heaven.
                 Kneeling down there I made the sign of the Cross and began to
              pray, determined, at any cost, to obtain my cure, provided it were in
                                             79]]></page><page Index="92"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO


          accordance with the will of God. The pain was then at its worst, but
          at the moment I was saying the words: "Sed libera nos a malo," the
          aching pain suddenly ceased. My blood resumed its usual course, the
          face assumed its natural proportions and I found myself cured and at
          ease, without any trace remaining to remind me of the agony I had
          suffered. How can I express the gratitude I then felt, and will ever
          feel, towards young Savio! What esteem do I not furthermore owe to
          him, who so speedily cured my body, for the good done to my soul!
             I beg you to take this account into consideration, and make use of
          it in such a manner as  you may judge  most suited to promote the
          glory of God, and confidence in the holy youth Dominic Savio.

                                   Obediently yours,
                                 MATTHEW GALLEANO, of Caramangna.



              THE TESTIMONY OF A MOTHER CONCERNING HER
                                   SON'S CURE.

             My only son had been lying sick in the hospital of SS. Maurice and
          Lazarus  for nearly a month. The cause of his illness was a rush of
          blood  to  the  brain,  which  made  him  delirious.  Amongst  other
          circumstances of his illness, one deserving of special remark was that
          nothing  could  make  him  utter  a  word.  No  one  can  imagine  the
          sorrow of a mother who beholds her  only son a prey to a disease
          which shows no hope of being cured. In my advanced years I should
          have been left without help of any kind, and my life, in consequence
          would have been a most unhappy one.
             One day, when under the weight of the deepest sorrow, I went
          with some relatives to the hospital. Whilst we were by the patient's
          bed, I heard how many times he had been bled, and at the sight of
          the death-like pallor and emaciation of his features, I burst into tears
          and nothing seemed able to console me. But thanks be to God, Who
          deigned to comfort me in an unexpected manner and to change my
          sorrow  into  the  greatest  consolation!  Some  little  distance  off  I
          noticed a young man with a small book in his hands; he went to a bed
          next  to  the  one  where  my  son  was  lying,  and  having  opened  the
                                         80]]></page><page Index="93"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO


              book, showed to the patient a picture of a boy about fifteen years of
              age,  whose  virtuous  life  was  related  in  the  book.  He  advised  the
              patient to read and to imitate the virtues of the boy who lived and
              died like a saint. At the sight of the book and the picture I thought at
              once that the boy represented in it was some saint, and approaching,
              I said to the one who held the book in his hands, "for the love of
              God and of Our Blessed Lady give me one of those books for my
              son." He answered that he would willingly do so, but that it would be
              useless  to  give  it  to  one  in  delirium  to  read,  and  that  it  would  be
              better for him to recommend himself to Dominic Savio, imploring
              him to obtain his cure. I at once approved of the proposal, and going
              close to my son I said to him in a faltering voice: "My son; listen,
              recommend yourself to Dominic Savio so that he may obtain your
              cure from God." At these words he turned towards me, but remained
              for a few moments motionless. Then suddenly, to the great surprise
              of  those  standing  by  and  to  my  great  consolation  he  said:  "I
              recommend  myself  to  him."  Words  will  not  express  the  joy  and
              satisfaction  which  my  heart  experienced  on  hearing  the  voice of  a
              son,  whose  cure  I  had  almost  despaired  of,  on  hearing  that  voice
              which  for  eighteen  days  had  not  sounded  in  my  ears.  I  then
              endeavoured  to  make  him  understand  the  holiness  and  virtues  of
              Savio, to whom we had both earnestly appealed.
                 Shortly  afterwards  there  was  a  complete  change,  and  he  was
              entirely cured from a disease which the doctors declared could only
              end in death or the asylum.

                                                                MARY PAIRA.
                 (Turin, April 10th, 1860).


                               SUDDEN CURE OF RUPTURE.

                 Amongst other favours obtained after recourse to Dominic Savio,
              the wonderful cure of a young  student deserves to be recorded. I,
              myself  and  many  others  were  witnesses of  this  fact,  which  is  here
              described by the recipient of the favour.
                 Three years ago I suffered from rupture, and though cured of it, I
              had undergone intense pain on that account. But on February 20th of
                                             81]]></page><page Index="94"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO


          this  year  (1860),  I  was  attacked  by  the  same  complaint  whilst  at
          recreation in the playground. I could not stand and was put to bed
          suffering  intensely.  The  doctor  was  sent  for,  and  at  his  advice,
          everything  was  prepared for another operation; a carriage  was  sent
          for to convey me to the hospital. The pain I was suffering at this time
          was too great to bear, and a sort of delirium took possession of me;
          some thought, in fact, that I was surely dying.
             But it was just then that I thought of our deceased companion,
          Dominic Savio. I had read his life and knew all about the favours he
          had obtained, so I appealed to him, saying: "If it be true that you are
          in heaven, obtain some relief for me in this illness." I then recited in
          his honour an Our Father, Hail Mary, and Glory be to the Father.
             I  had  scarcely  finished  the prayers,  when  a  peaceful  calm  came
          over me, and brought on a refreshing, sleep. But after a short time, I
          was  awakened  by  those  who  had  been  sent  for  to take  me  to  the
          hospital. To their surprise I said: "My pain has all gone." They found
          that I was perfectly cured, and had it not been growing late, I should
          have got up again from bed. However, on the following morning all
          traces of my attack had disappeared, and I arose with the others in
          the best of health.
             I  desire  to  offer  my  tribute  of  deep  gratitude  to  this  faithful
          Servant of God.

                                             CHARLES BELLINO (Aosta).


                                  A DOUBLE CURE.

             The Very Rev. Don Rua, the first successor of Don Bosco, gives
          the following account:
             A signal favour was obtained through the intercession of Dominic
          Savio  in  the  town  of  Chieri.  A  man,  named  Charles  Bechio,  had
          suffered  for  three  years  with  a  very  serious  rupture.  He  could  not
          apply himself to any work, for as soon as he made the slightest effort,
          the pain became so acute that he could not stand on his feet. He had
          already applied all the remedies suggested by doctors and surgeons,
          but the illness only increased.
             At  the  beginning  of  this  year  he  chanced  to  read  the  life  of
                                         82]]></page><page Index="95"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO


              Dominic Savio, and learning that many sick people had been cured
              by him, even instantaneously, he felt his faith and confidence revive,
              and hoped to be favoured in the same way. He began a novena at
              once for this end, and promised that if he were cured, he would go to
              Don Bosco to attest the fact. In the very beginning of the novena he
              noticed that his pains were diminishing, and an improvement had set
              in.  After  three  days  he  put  aside  his  truss,  and  by  the  end  of  the
              novena  was  perfectly  cured,  so  that  he  could  again  undertake  his
              work, which was of a very vigorous and tiring nature. It was then the
              month of March, and from that time has not been in the slightest
              pain.
                 Moreover,  Dominic  did  not  only  obtain  for  him  this  temporal
              favour, but a spiritual one as well, of greater consequence. For some
              years he had not approached the Sacrament of Penance, and felt such
              a repugnance to do so, that nothing but a special grace would have
              been  able  to  conquer  it.  Accordingly  he  had  recommended  this
              intention also to Dominic, and when his novena was over, all his old
              repugnance  and  hesitation  disappeared,  and  he  felt  a  desire  of
              drawing  near  to  God.  In  fact  he  approached  the  Sacraments  of
              Penance and Holy Communion to his great consolation.
                 The undersigned has  taken this  down from the recipient of the
              grace, who is ready to make any attestation required.

                                                       MICHAEL RUA (Priest).
                 (Turin, March 10th. 1861).


                     CURE OF A SERIOUS AFFLICTION OF THE EYES.

                 A matter of great importance urges me to write to you. During
              January of this year, I had been troubled with a painful malady of the
              eyes, and having tried all material remedies in vain, I determined to
              have  recourse  to  a  spiritual  one.  Remembering  your  former  pupil,
              Dominic  Savio,  and  the  many  graces  obtained.  for  those  who
              invoked  his  intercession,  I  had  recourse  to  him  also.  It  was  on
              January 19th, and whilst in the act of prayer, it seemed that he bathed
              my eyes in some miraculous manner, and from that moment the pain
              ceased and my sight became quite clear and strong.
                                             83]]></page><page Index="96"><![CDATA[JOHN BOSCO


             It is my earnest wish that the foregoing should be added to the
          accounts  of  other  miracles  worked  by  God  for  the  glory  of  his
          servant.

                                                  LAURENCE PELAZZA.
             (Carmagnola, April 1861).



                       A DANGEROUS ILLNESS OVERCOME.

             Having been requested by a number of prudent persons to inform
          you of a cure obtained through the intercession of Dominic Savio, I
          would ask you to add it to the other accounts sent to you.
             In July 1871, I was attacked by such a violent cough that I could
          get  no  rest  either  night  or  day.  The  doctor  was  sent  for,  and  he
          consulted others, but there was no sign of improvement. After some
          days I was evidently growing weaker and was troubled with catarrh,
          which  made  breathing  impossible.  Acute  bronchitis  set  in.  I  was
          unable  to  do  anything  but  a  little  reading,  and  so  I  picked  up
          Dominic Savio's life, although it was already familiar to me.
             His  virtuous  life,  and  the  favours  he  had  obtained,  naturally
          suggested to me that I should have recourse to him in my illness, and
          I began a triduum or three days of prayer. When the doctor came next
          he found such a marked improvement, that he said it could not be
          due to human aid or power. "It seems like an illusion," he said. The
          cough that had been racking me for three months was gone, together
          with the bronchitis which was slowly wearing me away; now, instead,
          I go about with sound and robust health, blessing Savio for obtaining
          such a signal favour.

                                               J. B. PELLEGRINI (Como).






                                         84]]></page><page Index="97"><![CDATA[LIFE OF DOMINIC SAVIO

                 Such is the Ven. Don Bosco's narrative of the Life of Dominic
              Savio, and of some of the favours obtained through his intercession.
              These  favours  have  been  multiplied  in  the  years  that  have  passed;
              they  have  been  influential  in  the  progress  of  the  Cause  of  his
              Canonisation, which was  formally introduced at Rome in February
              last (1914). Much has been written about Dominic Savio, particularly
              since that event, but we may well conclude by giving the Reader the
              words  of  His  Eminence  the  late  Cardinal  Parocchi,  who  wrote  in
              1895: "May the young learn from Savio how to sanctify themselves,
              even in the midst of dangers, how to join holiness with cheerfulness,
              frankness  with  reserve,  dignity  with  modesty,  the  interior  life  and
              intimate union with Our Lord with the diligent exercise of external
              duties; let them learn of him to be beloved by God and men, and
              thus to leave a holy memory to succeeding generations."



                                            FINIS.
























                                             85]]></page><page Index="98"><![CDATA["Let  u s   leave  a saint  to write the  life  of a saint,"  is   said  to
               have  been  the  exclamation  of  the  Angelic  Doctor  S t.
              Thomas  Aquinas,  when  he  entered  the cell  of his  brother
              doctor, S t .  Bonaventure, and found him absorbed in writing
              the life of his spiritual father, S t.  Francis. The peculiar value
              of the present  little book is   that  it  may  be said  once more
              to present the spectacle of a saint writing the life of a saint.
              Only whereas  in  S t.  Bonaventure's  case  a son  was writing
              the life of a father,  in this case we have the unique example
              of a father writing the life of his spiritual son. The writer, the
              saintly  Don  Bosco,  h a s   already  been  declared  Venerable,
              and the process for his  Beatification is   proceeding in  Rome.
              - Preface.































                                                           1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1









                                                           781304]]></page></pages></Search>